<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>What the possession of the living faith is, and the fruits thereof and wherein it hath been found to differ from the dead faith of the world, in the learning and following of Christ in the regeneration with an opening of light to all sorts of people that waits for the Kingdom of God, and a candle lighted to give the sight of the good old way of God, from the wayes that now ensnares the simple : also a message from the spirit of truth unto the holy seed who are chosen out of the world, and are lovers and followers of the light / written by J.N. in the time of his imprisonment, and now (the second time) published by a Friend.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12493109</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12493109</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62425</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62425)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 769:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>What the possession of the living faith is, and the fruits thereof and wherein it hath been found to differ from the dead faith of the world, in the learning and following of Christ in the regeneration with an opening of light to all sorts of people that waits for the Kingdom of God, and a candle lighted to give the sight of the good old way of God, from the wayes that now ensnares the simple : also a message from the spirit of truth unto the holy seed who are chosen out of the world, and are lovers and followers of the light / written by J.N. in the time of his imprisonment, and now (the second time) published by a Friend.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
                  <author>R. T. (Rebecca Travers), 1609-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 84 [i.e. 83], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Author's name appears in the work.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: R.T. (i.e Rebecca Travers)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62425:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62425:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>WHAT THE POSSESSION OF THE Living Faith IS, And the fruits thereof, And wherein it hath been found to differ from the dead Faith of the World, in the learning and following of Chriſt in the Regeneration.</p>
            <p>With an opening of Light to all ſorts of People that waits for the Kingdom of God;</p>
            <p>And a Candle Lighted to give the ſight of the good Old Way of God, from the wayes that now enſnares the ſimple.</p>
            <p>Alſo a Meſſage from the Spirit of Truth unto the Holy Seed, who are choſen out of the World, and are lovers and followers of the Light.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J. N.</hi> in the time of his Impriſonment, and now (the ſecond time) publiſhed by a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62425:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:62425:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
DEAR Friends and People, to whom this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Treatiſe may come, I ſaw, and felt it meet, that ſomething might be declared of the Author thereof, who was Cenſured, Judged, Condemned and cruelly perſecuted, by them that knew him not; yet they that had the knowledge of him, and were conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with him for ſome years before, in the time of his ſufferings, can with me bear witneſs, (and that not a few) that he came amongſt us in the ſpirit and power of <hi>Elias,</hi> and mighty works were wrought by him, and an effectual dore was opened, and many were turned unto God, and gathered into the feeling of that power, in which he was, and of which he teſtified, and it abides for ever, the fountain and giver of every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect gift, of whom he had received liberally grace for grace, and of his fulneſs did he manifeſt, not onely in words and writings, in and of the truth, but in his converſation, which was holy, harmleſs and undefiled, as one Redeemed out of the earth, in the heavenly was his dwelling, and no other Inheritance did he ſeek: And though ſpirits of all ſorts did beſet him, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and ſnares of all were laid for him, yet the Covetous and Wanton found nothing in him; for over the world he kept in the holy faith, which gained the victory, and a Conqueror he died, and lives for ever in that life which is everlaſting, of which he testified, and called many to, and thoſe that received his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and abide therein, are come to the Church of the firſt-born, where we have fellowſhip with him in that spirit that quickens the dead, and brought to life
<pb facs="tcp:62425:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in whoſe ſuffering and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection he had fellowſhip, and in him was he found, therefore the world hated him; and that they might fill up their meaſure of unrighteouſneſs, by him were they tried, who being tempted out of the body, become a ſign unto them that had and did reſiſt the ſubſtance, and in the dark they acted, and brought forth a cruel Decree, without Law, Reaſon or Witneſs, that he had ſaid or done any thing contrary to Juſtice, Law, Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or Decree of God or Men: But thoſe that had rejected the Light, brought forth this dark Concluſion, that becauſe he did not condemn what ſome others, whom they ſuppoſed had ſpoke blaſphemy, therefore he was a Blaſphemer: Truly I never could (in my own diſpoſition) rejoyce to trample on any fallen, (though an enemy) but being come to ſee the fulfilling of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Propheſies, (ſpoke by the Servants of the Lord) of the woes, wrath, and juſt overturnings that would unavoidably come on ſuch, who reſiſted the Light, I cannot but confeſs to his righteous judgments, that hath given them of their own doings, and covered them with darkneſs, who loved darkneſs better than light; though my ſoul deſireth that thoſe of them, that yet have abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Earth, might come to repentance, now the juſt puniſhment of their doings being brought upon them, who were themſelves in the Blaſphemy, who ſaid they were Chriſtians and were not, ſaid they would give liberty of conſcience, but did not; cried out againſt perſecution, and yet perſecuted. It is the Hypocrite that did and doth blaſpheme, that ſeems to be and is not: For theſe was, and is reſerved the blackneſs of darkneſs, and it encreaſed upon them who loved it
<pb facs="tcp:62425:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
better than light, and over-turned and over-whelmed are they by it, and ſhallnever come from under it, nor have dominion over it, but by the riſing of that light, to which and in which he teſtified, whom they thought not worthy to live, and therefore found out and invented puniſhment much worſe then an outward death. But <hi>Light ſprings for the righteous:</hi> And in thoſe years of his cruel and cloſe confinement, as he ſaw, felt and learned, he gave forth, for the raiſing and strengthning of the immortal Seed, (that many do, and Nations to come ſhall bleſs God for) and by the everlaſting Power (which his Perſecutors reſiſted) he overcame, and was gathered into the communion of the body (which the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy neither did nor do diſcern) and ſo drank into the one Cup of new Wine in the Kingdom of the Father, though in thoſe years of his cruel cloſe impriſonment, as he hath declared, he comba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d with all ſpirits, and was under the waters, and beheld the foundations of the Earth, and paſsed by the gates of Hell, and ſpirits of darkneſs in the night-ſeaſon ſurrounded him, and under the earth he paſſed, and deaths he knew many, and when the weight of the Mountains was upon him, his Friends and Acquaintance ſtood afar of him, and it was to be ſo, and he declared w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> felt the weight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was to be ſepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed from his Brethren: and that if any one, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> life in God, retain ſin on Earth, it is retained in Heaven. So that Power that led him through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he many temptations and trials, made him a living example of lowlineſs and ſubjection, not onely confeſſing wherein he had grieved any in the day he was tempted, but in the ſpirit of forgiveneſs he ſought to be forgiven, even of thoſe that had been b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb facs="tcp:62425:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by him; ſo he were a father, To Babes he did and could ſtoop, that the Spirit of love and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs might riſe over all, for he loved Juſtice and Righteouſneſs, and bore teſtimony thereunto, that that was and would be the ſtrength of thoſe that abode therein, being delivered from that which had preſſed him down, in the liberty and power of the free Spirit, he often ſpake of the ſubtilty and wickedneſs of that ſpirit that works in the Air, with which he had been beſet, ond what it led to, and the end thereof to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. So he viſited (after his enlargement) many of that ſort, and often propheſied, as of many things, which we have ſeen come to paſs, that they would turn into the earth, or to liberty and ranting, which his Soul abhorred, and therefare often ſpoke and writ againſt the workings of thoſe ſpirits, in what appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſoever, and to holineſs in ſoul, body and ſpirit, called he; and for the removal of that which hindred, was his travel to the laſt day of his viſible being among men. And as at firſt he appeared in this great City in the power of an endleſs life, togather us unto God, in the unity of the light and fellowſhip of the Goſpel, to the bringing forth of all vertue, in Brotherly kindne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and unfeigned love; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame he paſsed out of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> City (but a few days before he laid down the body) in perfect peace, returning to the Father who ſent him, and in whoſe will he brought forth unto God, and his works follow him. This and ſeveral others that he penned have formerly been printed, and ſome have given praiſe unto God for the benefit received thereby.</p>
            <p>And now out of a ſincere deſire that God over all may be glorified (from whom every good and perfect gift
<pb facs="tcp:62425:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cometh) and the ſouls that are yet afar off from the life of righteouſneſs may be brought nigh, is this again pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; And in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eling of the everlasting ſpirit, the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifier of all that believe, therein is it ſent abroad, by her that is a traveller for the breaking of the head of wickedneſs, and the opening of the eyes of the ignorant, and that the ſimple may not ſtumble at the Authors name, but read this or any other of his Writings, in Gods fear, that thou may receive counſel, instruction, wiſdom and comfort thereby, as many, who believe, have done. I have here ſet down his own words, as they were written by him, and ſent unto the Parliament: Concerning Chriſt Jeſus, that you may not be harmed or hindred by falſe reports, but receive the truth in the love of it, in which it is ſent to you in the good will of God, from her that is made willing to be a ſervant for Chriſts ſake,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <head>This following Teſtimony was written by his own hand, and delivered to the then Parliament, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him as a Blaſphemer, in the time of his impriſonment in Bridewel.</head>
            <p>CHriſt Jeſus, the <hi>Immanuel,</hi> (of whoſe ſufferings the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptutes declares) him alone I confeſs before men, for whoſe fake I have denied what ever was dear to me in this world, that I might win him, and be found in him, and not in my ſelf, whoſe life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd vertue I find daily manifeſt in my mortal body, (which is my eternal joy and hope of glory) whom alone I ſeek to ſerve in ſpirit, ſoul and body, night and day, (according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace working in me) that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e he may be glorified whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:62425:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by life or death: and for his ſake I ſuffer all things, that he alone may have the glory of my change, whoſe work alone it is in me: Even to that eternal Spirit be glory, and to the Lamb for ever.</p>
            <p>But to aſcribe this Name, power and vertue to <hi>James Nailor,</hi> (or to that which had a beginning, and muſt return to duſt) or for that to be exalted or worſhiped, to me is great Idolatry, and with the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus in me it is condemned: which Spirit leads to lowlineſs, meekneſs and long-ſuffering.</p>
            <p>So having an opportunity given (with readineſs) I am willing in the fear of God the Father (in honour to Chriſt Jeſus, and to take off all offences from every ſimple heart) this to declare to all the world, as the truth of Chriſt is in me, without guile or deceit, daily finding it to be my work to ſeek peace in truth with all men in that Spirit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>James Nailor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The Heads of the particulars contained in this enſuing Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>What the Poſſeſſion of the living faith is.</hi> pag. 1.</item>
               <item>II. <hi>Who they be that are under the Law and who they be that have made void the Law againſt themſelves, and who they be that are under grace.</hi> p. 24.</item>
               <item>III. <hi>Of the way of life from the knowledge that devoures the life.</hi> p. 26.</item>
               <item>IV. <hi>An opening of light to all ſorts of Rulers and people that wait for the Kingdom of God.</hi> p. 27.</item>
               <item>V. <hi>A Candle lighted to give the ſight of the good old way of God at his coming from the wayes that now enſnares the ſimple.</hi> p. 42.</item>
               <item>VI. <hi>The Living God glorified in his Temples, the true worſhippers that worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> p. 50.</item>
               <item>VII. <hi>To the Ranters.</hi> p. 57.</item>
               <item>VIII. <hi>Deceipt diſcovered by its fruits.</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>IX. <hi>A Meſſage from the Spirit of Truth unto the Holy ſeed.</hi> p. 69.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62425:5"/>
            <head>What the Profeſſion of the Living Faith is, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as a right Faith is the onely ground of mans Eternal happineſs, and the only thing which gains the Creature an entrance towards his Creator, and without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God; though much hath been ſaid of it already, yet I having found by learning the true and living faith which hath the living power, different from that faith, which is dead and without that power; And ſeeing that ſo many at this day are at eaſe in a dead faith, and their ſouls in the grave, In tender love thereto I am ſtirred up to declare ſomething of the faith of Chriſt which I have found onely effectual to Salvation and Reconciliation with God. And ſomewhat the rather in regard the Enemy hath ſpread ſo many falſe reports of me touching my faith in Chriſt Jeſus, which here I ſhall declare in plainneſs, for the ſatisfying of ſimple minds who deſire to know Truth rather then to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach it; and for thoſe who ſeek occaſion, I chuſe rather to bear their reproach that are in that Nature, then contend therewith, for my work is not with Fleſh and Bloud, nor is it in my Spirit to ſtrive with any about words, that ſtir up ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and contention and edefie not, but with God I ſtrive dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to that of God in all I ſeek to be manifeſt, which reſiſts not evil, but ſeek to overcome it with good, waiting for the Kingdom of God in all, and the Souls Redemption out of death, and the Seed out of bondage, and where that is not effected in meaſure, I look not to be owned, nor my witneſs received, though it be not of my ſelf, but Chriſt Jeſus in me.</p>
            <p>And firſt a Faith or belief I have found in the World, of which I ſhall ſay little in this place having found indeed lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in it to the Salvation of Life: Its a literal Faith, ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Hiſtory of the Scripture, touching God and Chriſt, and what Chriſt did in that Temple which the Jewes deſtroyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. But doth not know him in Spirit, nor believe him as his Name is EMANUEL to all Generations, and ſo doth not neceſſarily work the believer into a conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to that head, in his then walking, by his coming again in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62425:6"/>
the ſame Spirit and Power, working in them the ſame Will, Mind, and Affections, and Obedience to the Father in their meaſure which was in him the Example, Author, Worker and Finiſher of the True and Living Faith.</p>
            <p>And of this Faith (being ſomewhat dreſſed by the ſeveral Opinions of men) are all the unclean Spirits living in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever abomination is to be mentioned in the world, all Sects and Opinions, or whatever may be found in all Colours in theſe Northern Parts of the World, with this Faith they are covered, and this is their ſtrength, and here they take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to themſelves againſt all Reproof wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in or from without, though living openly in the greateſt Whoredomes againſt the Spirit of Holineſs, Carnal or Spiritual that can be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, even at a diſtance from Chriſt in his whole life; yet they believe Chriſt came to ſave ſinners, of which they are chief; and they that are whole need not the Phyſician, &amp;c. And ſo the greater their wickedneſs is, the nearer to Chriſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; And by this Faith he that came to ſave People from ſin, and to lead out of ſin both by Example and Spirit, is made a cover for all filthineſs of fleſh and Spirit, and to ſtrengthen the heart of wickedneſs againſt the life of holineſs; ſome in one ſin ſome in another; but with this Faith do all ſorts ſtrengthen themſelves and hardens their hearts againſt the light of Chriſt and that Spirit which reproves the World of ſin and convinceth of it, and would lead out of it; and hence it is that the witneſs of God that is holy in all, is trampled under foot in all, and little regarded in any, but by this Faith believed on in none to be the way to the Father, though the world have no light but it, nor is there a Promiſe of Life in any other: And this to me appears to be that Faith of the Devil or dead Faith the Apoſtle ſpeaks on, <hi>James</hi> 2. Though more hardned in it againſt Gods fear; for the Devils when they believe tremble at it; So this Faith I leave, being judged already by its fruits with the light of Chriſt in every honeſt heart that loves holineſs.</p>
            <p>And of that Faith I ſhall ſpeak ſomething, in which I have found a meaſure of the Life of Chriſt made manifeſt in my mortal Body, in which life alone is the True and Eternal uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and atonement with the Holy God, into whom no unclean
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62425:6"/>
thing can enter. And this is not a notion of what was done in another generation paſt or to come, hundreds or thouſands of years diſtance, but that which leads to the beginning of the work of a new Creature at this day, and a new birth ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally begotten and born and brought to light, without which none can ſee the Kingdom of God nor enter therein; And this Faith doth not work by the comprehenſions of brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that becauſe I could here conceive or declare of Chriſt Jeſus, from the beginning to the age thereof in words or thoughts, that therefore I have learned him, or know him as I ought to do, or am grown up in him to a perfect man, and ſo to deceive others by declaring and boaſting of what God hath not wrought in me, as a man may eaſily do and deceive his own ſoul and bewitch others alſo, by leading them out of their meaſures of Gods preſent work in them. But of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Father w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h now worketh powerfully in ſpirit by love thereto, the myſtery wherof is holden forth in a pure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, working out the old leven, purifying the heart &amp; making all things new, judging and killing and crucifying with Chriſt in ſpirit the works of the fleſh, and caſting out every thing in me that is not of God, and renewing in me the things of God in their order by his mighty working in me, in which the ſoul is raiſed out of the grave, and the dead reſtored to life, actually and not in conceit. Of the Grounds and Workings of this Living Faith I ſhall ſpeak ſomething.</p>
            <p>And though the foundation of this Faith or beginning of it was, that I did really believe in that which Chriſt did and ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and that there in that veſſel he bare the ſins of the World, and ſatisfied the wrath of God for ſins paſt, and overcame death, hell, and the grave, and made way for the Seed to ariſe in all through the whole World who would believe in his light which then ſhined through him to all men, wherein he might be ſeen to be the Way, the Truth, and the Life apparent, openly triumphing over all that had paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Seed. And much more might be ſaid of him there finiſhed, all which I did believe according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cripture, which was an opening of me to receive him from Heaven in the ſame ſpirit and power, without which I could not have received the gift of that holy Spirit, God having ſo purpoſed from the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62425:7"/>
beginning, that the Covenant of Eternall Life and power ſhould be received no other way but by faith in him who in the fulneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime was there manifeſt in fleſh, for the taking away ſins paſt, and making a way for the Reſurrection of life over all, to ſave from ſins for time to come.</p>
            <p>The effect of which Faith when in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ight I firſt received it, did turn my mind out of all my ſins paſt, and took my mind out of them, and turned me towards God, and holineſs of life I then believed to attain in that faith, and receive power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to grow up in him to his fulneſs and ſtature, which then I ſee no leſs faith could ſave me then the perfect Faith of the Son of God, which before I had not received, but then received with ſuch gladneſs of heart, that it ſet my face and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights out of all ſin towards the perfection of Chriſt, in which I then believed, which was the Joy then ſet before me; yet was not the work done and finiſhed in me already, though (I having received the Faith and Hope of the Son of God, and was turned from all my former ſin and my own righteouſneſs, ſo that) if I had departed this Body, I had died in no leſs Faith then the Holy Faith of Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo being turned to his Spirit out of the works of the Fleſh, I was turned from my ſin, and ſo from condemnation, yet was there a great work to do in me before I could witneſs freedom from the body of death, and the root and ground of evil removed, and the ſeed raiſed to reign, and the ſoul brought into the holy City, the reſurrection of the dead, and fellowſhip in the Father and the Son &amp;c. And that glorious liberty of the new Creature, and all things to be of God in me, as the Scriptures do witneſs; ſo this faith did not work me into a conceit of my ſelf, glorying in knowledge, and ſo to become a Teacher of others what I had conceived below the life, but it led me down into the obedience of the Spirit of Light, to wait therein for the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Life, and I came to ſee in that Light that the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſin did ſtill work from the old ground and root, and that muſt be removed by the power of Chriſt working in ſpirit, and my obedience and watchful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs therein was required, and that without obedience to this faith I could not come to perfect victory over the enmity nor the glorious liberty of the Sons of God; for though this faith had turned my heart towards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62425:7"/>
Chriſt, and given me hope to attain him, yet I had not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n learned him, nor was he yet formed in me, ſo was I led in the Light of Chriſt, to ſee what I had of this treaſure in the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en veſſel. which I found to be in me very little, and that Seed the leaſt of all Seeds; ſo I became little in that eye which told me the truth, though I had been high in my own thoughts formerly.</p>
            <p>And ſo to the Word of the beginning of Chriſt I was led, or the firſt Principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt, that with that which teacheth Chriſt, I might learn Chriſt in every meaſure of him as I grew therein; ſo was I brought to know him that was made under the Law, and to the foundation of repentance from dead works, and to doctrines of Baptiſms, and to Eternal Judgement; then came I in Truth and Life to ſee what they were doing whom the Apoſtles exhorted to work out their own Salvation with fear and trembling, after they had fully believed what Chriſt had done for them at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in that Veſſel, and many other Scriptures did he open to me as I learned him, which before to me was a Myſtery, while I learned them in meanings without the Life of Chriſt, which then was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt as they came to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in me, being led by the ſame Spirit in that work of Faith; then came I to ſee that I through the Law muſt be redeemed from the Law, and that my redemption from it muſt not be by making it void, but by fulfilling of it, and till then it had power over me, and ſin took occaſion by it to ſtrengthen it ſelf in me; but as I came to grow in the Spirit and Power of Chriſt, I was in him brought through it, it in him fulfilled, and I dead to it as it came to be fulfilled, and the words of Chriſt I found true, <hi>I came not to break the Law, but to fulfil it,</hi> and it is eaſier for Heaven and Earth to paſs away then one jot of the Law to paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away till it be fulfilled, and I needed not a meaning to that Scripture, but a fulfilling thereof in Chriſt Jeſus; and the Schoolmaſter that brings to Chriſt I learned, and Chriſt formed, &amp; the heir under tutors, before I knew the liberty of the Son of God or perfect freedom, and then I ſaw the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures could not be broken nor wreſted, but it muſt be learned in the life of it to Salvation, which the unlearned wreſt to their own deſtruction by meanings without life, and that it was of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62425:8"/>
no private interpretation, but this one Spirit muſt open it all in the fulfilling thereof, and this Faith in Chriſt Jeſus onely was able to make wiſe unto Salvation of Eternall Life.</p>
            <p>And then came I clearly to ſee Chriſt Jeſus ſet before me in all things that I was to go through, in that faith which I had firſt received, and that the attaining of him was the hope of glory, and no hope without him; and this hope was as an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor in all hardſhips and temptations, which was not a few, I was led through but all was counted little while I ſtood in this Faith, for the hope that was in me to win Chriſt; and I clearly ſaw that notwithſtanding my firſt faith in what he had done at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yet if I did not continue therein to follow the ſame ſpirit in obedience thereto, believing therein, in all its leadings, hoping to attain to Chriſt Jeſus the end of that Faith, in daily growing towards his Stature and fulneſs, but had turned aſide, or ſet down ſhort of the leadings of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the way, I had made void my hope of Glory, the work of my redemption, and that which Chriſt did at <hi>Jeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alem</hi> (as to me) and had denyed my firſt Faith, and could not have been ſaved from wrath to come. That being the end of that Faith committed to me, that therein I might faithfully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting follow him in Spirit through all Tryals and Temptations, of which way he was a perfect example in his walking in that Fleſh at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that through the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures I might have hope, ſeeing he went the ſame way before me there in which he now leads, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therein I might ſee him to be the ſame to all generations as he was there, and in his Saints that followed him. And as they exhorted one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to look unto him in their Travel, who was the Authour and Finiſher of their Faith, and to conſider him as an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who endured ſuch contradictions of ſinners againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, leaſt they ſhould be weary of ſuffering and faint in their mindes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o their Faith and Hope was ſtrengthened; So alſo I looking to the ſame in him, and alſo in them after him, my Faith and Patience might be doubled, and my obedience made without doubting, and my hope firme unto the end, which end was the winning Chriſt in me the Hope of Glory, the great Myſtery of Faith, which is hid from all till the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62425:8"/>
of Chriſt Jeſus; and ſo when the Saints and Apoſtles had Chriſt revealed in them, they were able Miniſters of him, and had the myſtery opened, and preached it without doubt; that myſtery of godlineſſe which was great, yet hid from the world, but to them without all controverſie, God manifeſt in fleſh, not God fleſh, but manifeſt in fleſh, which myſtery of Faith they held in a pure conſcience, and ſo I knew my Faith to be the ſame Faith once delivered to the Saints, and the good fight of that faith I came to know, and that Faith which overcomes the world, which hath the promiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of Eternal Life, which all that go back from denyes the Faith of Chriſt, and ſets up a Faith without Chriſt which is not the faith of Chriſt, and ſo in the learning of Chriſt I came to ſee the faith of Chriſt from faith to faith, and the faith of Devils, the living working faith, and the dead faith without works, and I finde that Chriſt never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that he could never be perfect nor overcome the Devil, nor overcome ſin; it was never the Faith of Chriſt to make void the Law of his Father unfulfilled in him; it was never his faith to revenge evil, but to overcome it with good; it was never his faith to reſpect perſons, or that he could commit ſin and not be the ſervant of ſin; it was never his faith to ſue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, or fight, or perſecute any, to judge for rewards, or Preach for hire, or any way to ſerve the Mammon of this world; it was not his Faith to obſerve his own will, his own times, or the worlds cuſtomes, but to obſerve his Father in all things, and onely what he received from him, that he did, and could do nothing of himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he never believed them to be chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God who ſaid and did not.</p>
            <p>And much ſuch like things as theſe were never by him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, but is the worlds faith to uphold them in ſin and luſts, who are enemies to the faith of Chriſt which preſents perfect to God by working out ſuch evils: All which I came to ſee, not by man, but in the revelation of Chriſt as in his Faith I learned him, growing into his Faith, into him and his life therein made manifeſt in my body: So I ſee what is his in truth as the truth is in Jeſus, and what is the worlds, and but called his to oppoſe him; And I ſee that which loves the things of this world to be none of his love, nor that his joy that takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in viſible things, nor that his liberty which is in the works
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62425:9"/>
of the fleſh, nor that his peace that is in ſin, nor that his patience that ſeeks its own revenge, nor that his glory that's in pride, nor that his worſhip which ſtands in carnal things, nor that his honour that's ſought of men, nor that his knowledge that's after the fleſh, nor that his fear that is taught by his precepts of men, theſe are in the world and not in him, but have onely got the name to be his, but are enemies to his life, and were never begat of his Father nor learned in the Son; all which and much like ſtuff I came to ſee the deceit of, by that truth and ſimplicity I found in Chriſt, contrary to the will of man.</p>
            <p>And ſo in the life of Chriſt I have learned to know the growth of the Faith of Chriſt and the riches of it, and the end of it, which is Chriſt Jeſus in all its working, and I alſo know the worlds faith, its uncleanneſs whoſe end is not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the holineſs of Chriſt in life, but would live in the worlds delights and have Chriſt for a cover, and be ſaved by the righteouſneſs of another, which they have no minde to walk in themſelves; and ſo that faith works not by love which loves not the life of Chriſt, but are enemies to his Croſſe, minding earthly things, and this is the earthly faith, but the living Faith works by love to holineſs of life, and therefore purifies the heart, and the myſtery of it ſtands in a pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience within themſelves that have it, and not in telling and comprehending what was in another, for the Devils be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the holineſſe that was in Chriſt and can preach it, but cannot inherit it, becauſe they love not to live the life of it, and by this I know them both for ever, and all that prove them in the life of Chriſt ſhall witneſſe with me, the end of the one is the life of Chriſt in which himſelf walked, and the ſame obedience of the ſame Spirit to the ſame Father by the ſame power, according to the proportion of Faith received from God, which Faith is from above, and ſo layes hold on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things for its ſtrength, and ſo brings forth heavenly fruits: The other profeſſeth and promiſeth great things, but ends in the world and mindes earthly things, and doth not purifie the heart, nor believes ever to attain the life of Chriſt, his ſtature or fulneſs, but counts it an error in ſuch as preſſe after ſuch attainments, and ſo the end of the converſation of one is Chriſt Jeſus to hold forth in Life and Power, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever: The end of the other is a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62425:9"/>
liberty to ſin here while they can take any pleaſure in it, and ſanctification and ſalvation when they are dead, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the end of each faith ſo it works, for its impoſſible for him that cannot believe holineſs to work holineſs, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to each mans faith ſo muſt he inherit in this world and that which is to come.</p>
            <p>And in the workings and attainments of this living power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful faith I have found ſeveral meaſures according to my growth therein, from the Word of the beginning of Chriſt or the firſt Principle of Chriſt, and the fulneſs, age and ſtature of Chriſt, as betwixt a Babe &amp; a man grown in ſtrength, &amp; much working in ſpirit I found betwixt faith received of Chriſt Jeſus, and Chriſt learned in me; for though I received the faith of his fulneſs in what he was at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in his fleſh there at once, yet had not I ſo learned him in Spirit &amp; life in my mortal fleſh nor put him on at once, but in the light of Faith I ſaw I was ſo to run as to win him before I could put him on, wherein I came to ſee and know my ſelf begotten again in him by faith towards God, who is the way to God, in which way I came to ſee the begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Father manife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in meaſure in me in the pure image of a Holy Child, ſeparate from the fleſhly ſinful ſeed, or Chriſt formed in me as the Scriptures witneſs, and when I did behold his pure image and his pure mind and nature ſo far contrary to my own, yet then was not he in his Kingdom nor all things put under his feet, nor could I ſay that Jeſus was then Lord in me, but by the Spirits working by this Faith I had received, and in hope thereof was I made to endure the loſs of all things, and to deny all things that ever this holy Spirit did War againſt in me, which might any way oppreſſe this holy plant or hinder its growth, owning his judgment in the light, upon what ever was in my heart or affections but him alone, though never ſo much gain in my account in the world, which judgment being owned &amp; conſented to againſt my ſelf and all my ſelf lovers, therein was I parted from them in judgment, and ſo then was they ſubdued by the powerful workings of that Spirit and put under his feet, and I ſet free from them to ariſe with him above them, being brought from under them, and this was not done all at once but in order as he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the light to manifeſt every particular evil; And as that Faith I had received wrought by love to him a conſent in my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62425:10"/>
ſpirit to his juſt judgement upon them, and I made willing to give them up to the fire, and to come out of them and joyn to him in the execution, leaſt he ſhould conſume me with them, as it muſt have been had I ſtayed in them, and here I found the benefit of the light which goes before his face to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his way, and the ſalvation of Faith which ſaved me through hope of him, that I was not deſtroyed in my ſins, which Faith and hope gave me an entrance within the vail, or a hiding place in him while the indignation was over, which was to paſs upon the man of ſin.</p>
            <p>And ſo a voice was heard in the wilderneſs, calling out of ſin into a way I knew not but as the light of his Covenant led me in the ſpirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> turning my heart towards him, that he might not ſmite the earth with a curſe at his coming, in which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ere I came into the Kingdom of Chriſt my pure reſt, I met with many hardſhips and great travels, and many temptations and tryals within and without, but the greateſt enemies was yet within me, which would upon every hardſhip be tempring with unbelief to deſtroy this Faith and hope, which was all that I had ſet before me to encourage me to endure ſuch hardſhips, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the light in a way I had not known, and to walk in the Cloud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to meet the Lord, and to leave my former knowledge and wiſdom, and glory and riches, to go in a way I had not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, and to abide ſuch aſſaults on every hand, every foot the world which I was called out of ready to overtake me and compaſſe me about, and to turn me back again into what I had ſeen and enjoyed, behind me, ever ſeeking to perſwade me that I ſhould never attain to him that was ſet before me in the Faith and hope; Then come I clearly to ſee, that though I had received the Faith of Chriſt as a ſhield in this War, by which I was ſaved that the wrath of God took me not away in theſe temptings and murmurings, and reaſonings and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which did ariſe in the fleſhly part, yet the purchaſed poſſeſſion was not yet redeemed for me to enjoy at preſent, though I had heard and believed the Goſpel of ſalvation, and was ſealed with the holy Spirit of promiſe till I came to be boilded up with Chriſt for an habitation of God through the Spirit. And I found by daily experience that my ſalvation was not compleat ſo long as my ſoul was ſubjected under any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62425:10"/>
earthly luſt or paſſion, nor the War over, but as by the mighty working of God in me by that Spirit this came to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued under the feet of Chriſt, and the Soul ſet above it with him to reign in the heavenly place; ſo was my Salvation nearer then when I believed, for the Soul is not ſafe while ſin lives, or the fleſh luſts, for that wars againſt the Soul, and every ſin wounds it, and this ſhall all know who are not paſt feeling, what ever their Faith be touching Chriſt Jeſus, or what was wrought in another, whilſt ſin defiles the Soul it is not ſafe, nor the honeſt heart hath peace and reſt, for the reſt and peace is placed in the Holy City where comes no unclean thing, into which the Soul enters not till that all righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs be fulfilled upon earth, &amp; the Soul ſingled from all corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and have put on immortality, &amp; death ſwallowed up in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, when the ſting is taken away, which is ſin, &amp; the ſtrength of ſin, which is the Law, which is not taken away but where it is fulfilled, there onely grace reigns through righteouſneſs, and this I found to be truth as the truth is found in Jeſus, as I came to learn him and put him on by Faith, which I had believed; and I ſee the folly of ſuch as would make void the Law by tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Faith and Grace, wherein ſin is yet ſtanding, and the Soul taken captive therewith, which I had often ſought peace therein to my ſelf, but could not inherit liberty to my Soul any other way but as it came to be purified in obedience through the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And this work was not wrought in me by the knowledge of Chriſt after the fleſh, but as I came to learn him in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for ſpiritual wickedneſs had taken my Soul captive, and by the Spirit it muſt be ſanctified and ſet free. And I came to ſee that if I had been in his company here on earth as long as his Diſciples were in the fleſh, and ſeen as much as they did, and heard from his own mouth, I ſhould have been ſhort of this work as they were, in whom the Child was unborn when he went away in the fleſh, and they knew not what Spirits they were of, untill he came again to them in Spirit and was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then could they preach the Reſurrection of the dead and the Souls Redemption, and deſired to know him no more after the fleſh, when once they had received him in Spirit, but Preached Chriſt within the Hope of Glory, who till then looked for an outward kingdom and glory, untill they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62425:11"/>
his promiſe, <hi>He that dwelleth with you ſhall be in you, I will not leave you comfortleſs, I will come unto you; the world ſeeth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no more, but ye ſee me, and becauſe I live, ye ſhall live alſo; at that day ye ſhall know that I am in my Father, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u in me, and I in you;</hi> And this was his promiſe, whom they received, whom the world ſeeth no more, whoſe expectations are carnal, neither can any ſee the Kingdom of Heaven but who are born of this Spirit and Heirs of this Life, and he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life, but the wrath of God abides upon him whatever he may ſay he believes, and none hath the Son but as they receive this Spirit, and are led by this Spirit, and born thereof. And this I found alſo, that this Son of God doth not appear in any within or without, but as he conforms them to his own Image, which he hath alwayes born in this world, as ſaith the Scripture, when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him, who ſhall change our vile bodies and make them like his glorious body, from glory to glory by the ſame Spirit; And herein we have boldneſs in the day of Judgment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as he is ſo are we in this preſent world; and this is not obtained with thoughts of believing without, but by a lively working Power, which works out the earthly image and nature, and conforms to the heavenly in that ſpiritual birth which is not of fleſh and blood, nor could fleſh and blood ever diſcern it in whom it was, but ever hared it in whom it hath appeared in all Ages; Which is of a ſhining nature where it is begotten of the Father, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be hid where it is formed, but by his fruits gives light to the world contrary to the worlds wayes, ſhowing of his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Judgment againſt the deeds of darkneſs; And this heavenly begetting of the Father is to be holden forth in that clear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mage of the Father, according to every ſeveral mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as he grows therein without mixture, that all may ſee that he is not of this world, who alſo takes them out of this world as he grows in any or they in him, forth of the world they muſt go, bearing his reproach, that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, they are not of this world, even as I am not of this world, and this is the worlds light and condemnation, even his coming. And ſo I find that Faith which joyns to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62425:11"/>
world where it is, and doth not overcome the world, is not the faith of Chriſt, nor layes hold on the power of Chriſt, though Faith may believe the Hiſtory of the Scriptures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt; which faith ſets not up the Kingdom of God in the heart, and caſts out the world there, that faith ſaves not the ſoul from the pollution of the world through luſt, and ſo is but a conceit of ſalvation, and not the power of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as ſaith the Scriptures: Whoſoever is born of God overcometh the world, and this is the victory that overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the world, even your faith; and the faith which works not thus, is like a body without a ſpirit which is dead; but the living faith that ſtands in Chriſt Jeſus, that ſpirit puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the heart and conſcience, and makes toward God in Chriſt the example in all good things, overcoming whatever would lett the appearance of Chriſt in his temple, or hinder the bringing forth his vertues which is believed to be in him, to the utmoſt of whatever he hath received of the Father for ſuch believers, who believes not in a lye, but in the truth and power of God as it is in Chriſt Jeſus and hath been decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Scriptures not for a diſcourſe, but for an inheritance of life, of whoſe fulneſs we all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceive according to our Faith. till his coming and we be compleat in him, and he in us; and ſo not come ſhort of the glory of God, the end of our Faith and Converſation, that to the world he may be manifeſt in life and power to be the ſame that ever he hath been, though he have appeared in ſeveral forms in the fleſh, yet one in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to make a compleat body.</p>
            <p>And therefore we finde thoſe who were of this Faith witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt preſent (which the worlds faith could never receive under any form or profeſſion, but counted it blaſphemy, and that ſpirit the ſpirit of the Devil.) And ſo <hi>Iſaiah</hi> witneſſed this Childe born to them that ſo believed in his time, who was the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whoſe Name they knew to be Immanuel, and this was before he appeared in that Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was called the Son of man before that time alſo; and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid he was revealed in him and ſpoke in him, and wrought in him, and in his fleſh that which was behinde of the afflictions of Chriſt was to be filled up for the bodies ſake which is the Church, and to whom
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62425:12"/>
he forgive any thing in his time, he forgive it in the perſon of Chriſt; and many more might be noted who confeſſed the ſame Chriſt in them preſent, both before and after his time at <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſalem,</hi> which teſtimony could never be received (by the wiſdom of the world) in his Temples, before nor then, nor ſince to this day, for the god of this world being king in the heart, and having blinded the eye of the minde that ſhould ſee his ſpiritual glory through the light of the Goſpel, he perſwades the world that he is either paſt or to come, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preſent; and as many as are brought to confeſs him before men finde it ſo at this day, who are hated of all men for his Names ſake, that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, and his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony finiſhed.</p>
            <p>And this faith which confeſſeth him preſent, is that which the world cannot bear nor receive, who will preach him them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at a diſtance, what he was and will be, but this faith cannot reach his coming at preſent in any meaſure to grow to his appearance now, nor will this faith ever give an entrance into his kingdom upon earth, nor the holy reſt, nor is this the Faith of Chriſt (that puts him thus afar off) which fills with all the fulneſs of God.</p>
            <p>And by what I have learned, this is clear to me for ever without any more Controverſie, That the faith that admits of ſin is not Chriſts Frith, nor hath any ſhare or poſſeſſion in him; that faith which is not holy came not from God, and ſo cannot build up to God; that is not ſaving Faith that doth not ſave from ſins, but is deceiving faith which deceives the Soul, and ſuffers luſt to defile it and deſtroy it, and ſo brings it under condemnation, by believing lyes, and ſo letting in ſin upon the Soul by conſent, perſwading that it cannot be otherwiſe; and ſo gives the Devil victory and the world vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and the fleſh victory, and ſin victory over the Soul, which ſhould give the Soul victory over all; And what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deceit can there be to the Soul then this is? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for ever that which I have ſeen and learned do I declare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, that this is the deceiving faith, and indeed rather unbelief then the Faith of Chriſt, which makes way for the god of this world to reign and act in things contrary to the life of Chriſt in the Creature, and the life of the Soul? and that faith
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62425:12"/>
which gives way to the leaſt ſin is not the Faith of Chriſt, whoſe work and coming is to deſtroy the works of the Devil, and redeem the Soul from ſin, and the leaſt meaſure of that Faith that ſtands in his life overcomes the world and ſin in that meaſure; and he that commits ſin goes out of that Faith, and acts againſt it; and a lying faith I have found that to be which perſwades the ſoul of freedome from condemnation, but gives it not freedom from ſin, which is the cauſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and all ſhall witneſs this with me now or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, that where ſin hath power, here death hath power, and the Grave, and Hell, and Condemnation hath power alſo, for theſe are the wages of ſin, then ſhall yon ſay you were deceived who believed the contrary; And may not ſuch truly be ſaid to be paſt feeling indeed, who can commit ſinne and feel no Condemnation for it already? And this is the effect of their falſe Faith, to harden themſelves againſt the faithful witneſs of God in their own Conſcience, and the ſeared Conſcience hath made ſhipwrack of the Faith of Chriſt, and the doctrine of devils preaches the faith of devils to give way to the works of the Devil, which all ſin is from the leaſt to the greateſt, and he that pleads for it is a Father to it, and he that commits it, a ſervant, and may look for the wages thereof if he repent not, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he believe the contrary.</p>
            <p>And many may feel this truth at this day, who have a long time believed with this faith, deceiving their own ſouls day u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day, believing they ſhall not be condemned, when they are condemned already i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their own hearts, and feel the weight of ſinne daily preſſing their Souls, and burthening the pure Conſcience, and the fear of death and ſinne keeps their Souls ſtill in bondage, and lies upon them all their lives, and yet they will force themſelves to believe, contrary to Holy Faith, and a good Conſcience, that they are ſaved and redeemed, and thus make ſhipwrack of ſaving Faith and a good Conſcience, by believing a lye, contrary to their own daily feeling, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to encourage them therein but this perſwaſion, which ſuits well with ſuch as take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe, which perſwaſion comes not of God, but condemned by that of God in themſelves; and this is the eſtate of many at this day, though ſome there be whoſe Conſciences are feared, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62425:13"/>
feel not this witneſs living in them, though their damnation ſlumbereth not, though they have loſt their Calling and Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo.</p>
            <p>And this have I learned in Chriſt, that there is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence both in effect and nature betwixt that Faith which is the gift of God, and that faith which men make to themſelves, for that which is the gift of God is of his own nature, clean, pure, and perfect are all his gifts, and ſo it works naturally the work and will of God in all who receive it freely, and mix nothing with it to darken it or ſtop his working; and by this Faith I am ſaved from ſin and condemnation, and begotten to the Father thereof in Chriſt Jeſus; which faith is not of my ſelf, but is the gift of God, to perfect holineſs in the ſight of God; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is done in this faith is not ſin, and whatſoever is againſt this Faith, or not of this Faith is ſin, and brings Condemnation, and this Faith approves not of it; and if I act nothing doubtingly nor againſt this holy Faith, in this Faith I am juſtified in my own heart, and my own Conſcience kept clean, and I approved in Gods ſight, and I have boldneſs through the obedience of Faith in the day of Judgement, that it is not my own work but the righteouſneſs of Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus, and this effect hath ſaving working Faith, and this is its Nature and Grace.</p>
            <p>But another Faith I have found which is not ſo in nature or effect, being not freely received from above, but is feigned and hath its ground here below, and its ends alſo: The earthly man in his wiſdom from the letter, or reaſon or comprehenſions, ſets up an Opinion or Image in his minde touching God or Chriſt, or Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Worſhip, Doctrine, or Manners, or any other thing and then looking upon the likeneſs of it in the reaſoning part, gathers ſtrength to believe it muſt needs be ſo, and ſo forms a faith in himſelf; And though this faith be not perfect when he hath formed it and made it with all his ſtrength; but many things in Scriptures and the practiſe of the Saints, but eſpecially that of God in his own Conſcience will not ſure with it yet the ſtrong man being above in the ſtrength of his Comprehenſion, forceth a Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all theſe and cauſes all to bow under it; ſo this Faith brings not forth the Birth of Chriſt, nor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62425:13"/>
his pure Image and Life, neither in Matter or Worſhip nor Manners but what he may imitate Chriſt and the Saints in worſhip and keep the world, and eſcape the Croſs, and ſave his life and credit and glory there, that he will conform to, and glory in, and for the reſt he believes it concerns not him now in all things at this day ſo to walk as they did; And as this Faith is not perfect in Worſhip, ſo in Practiſe alſo: for that evil he is not addicted to he condemns in all, but that which is in his own heart and eye, and brings him profit and pleaſure, that he will cover, and believes it may ſtand with true belief at this day though formerly it could not; And this is the Faith made after man and not after God, and ſo ſerves in reſpect of Perſons, Times, and Things, but bows not all theſe for ever to worſhip in Spirit, nor brings them under the foot of Jeſus that Spirit, but being earthly by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath earthly effects, and God doth not own that with his Power, nor goes forth with that which man makes, but with his own Gift, which is good and perfect in every meaſure thereof; And this alſo I have learned in Chriſt Jeſus, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to all that ſeek Faith in him, That I never received any meaſure of this Faith of Chriſt in vain, but whatever I acted or ſuffered therein, from the leaſt meaſure till this day, in it I prevailed, againſt what ever the light of the Spirit led me out therein, and a ſhield I have found it, and a growth in it towards Chriſt Jeſus in every work of it, wherein I have ſtood ſingle to the end, however tempted or tryed before the end appeared, yet in the end of that Faith I was ever a Conqueror through the Spirit, and whoever proves it to the end in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, ſhall be witneſs with me herein, with a Cloud of witneſſes that have gone before, who by this holy Faith have prevailed over the powers of ſin, and entred into the holy Reſt, who have not ſought their own Kingdom but the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And only this pure Faith which works towards the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſt in all actions and ſufferings, is that which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all things in their place and time, and fits all Relations for his appearance therein to glorifie God, for God is not glorified in any thing upon Earth but in which the Son ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, who is the expreſſe Image and Glory of God, and in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62425:14"/>
whom alone he Reveals himſelf and the glory of his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Mercy the Grace and Truth of God is in his face in whom ever he appears; And ſo every meaſure of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Faith works towards the heavenly appearance, and the earthly faith to the earthly appearance; And ſo Faith in God is that which works effectually by love to the Image and Life of God in this world, which is ſeen onely in his ſpiritual beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which being believed in and ſet above, ſhines forth in every meaſure, ſhewing the vertue and glory of the Spirit of God; but the famed earthly faith admits of ſome earthly thing in the heart for its end, in love to which it works diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Spirit, and ſo comes ſhort of the glory of God, for it cannot hold forth the fruits of the Spirit to glorifie God with an earthly lover in the heart, nor can one faith ſerve God and Mammon; ſo he that loves the things of this world is Gods enemy, whoſe faith withſtands the appearance of Chriſt in his actions or ſufferings, and ſo withſtands the glory of God which therein ſhould be manifeſt to all men, and this is that faith which ever of old hath put him afar off, yet gets the form and words to withſtand the life and vertue; And of this ſort they are of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks, having a form of godlineſs, but deny the power of godlineſs, who ever was the greateſt enemies to the coming of Chriſt, being not of the Faith of Chriſt, nor of the Spirit of Chriſt, but being from below, withſtands his coming from above to be brought forth in his vertue, or worſhipped in his Spirit; this is Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>And this ſpirit and this faith it is that wreſts the Scriptures to ſeduce from Chriſt, and deſtroy the way of his coming; and to that end what Chriſt really Commands to be brought forth of his life and vertue in real appearance, this ſpirit ſerves himſelf with a meaning, inſtead of ſerving Chriſt with real actual obedience; And ſo his birth is a meaning inſtead of the life of Chriſt, and this he ſets to oppoſe that life, leaſt it ſhould be born into the world; as for inſtance, when Chriſt ſaith in Scriptures, Him that ſmiteth thee on the one cheek offer him the other, and him that ſues thee and takes thy coat, forbid him not thy cloak alſo, and him that takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy goods ask them not again, reſiſt not evil, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62425:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
evil with good, and love them that hate you, and many ſuch like Commands which Chriſt means really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and led an example in himſelf; and who ever receives the ſame Spirit, it moves to the ſame things as it grows in any, and being obeyed will bring forth the ſame fruits to glorifie the Father thereof to all Generations, which Spirit waxeth not old, nor in its fruits barren, where it is really received in the Faith thereof and obeyed. But ſaith this other faith in the earthly ſpirit, Chriſt did not mean as he ſpoke, you muſt not take him litterally, thoſe words muſt have a ſpiritual meaning; and this ſpiritual meaning of his is to devour the life of this obedience both in Letter of Chriſt and Spirit of Chriſt, and to ſet up a ſubtle meaning without the life of Chriſt and contrary to his example, and this he will have to take place in all, both againſt the plain words of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in his walking, and the working of his Spirit in others; &amp; if he cannot deſtroy this faith and fruit before it be brought forth, then his work is to render him a high Blaſphemer, in whom this Child is born and brought forth to light, and counts it high preſumption for any to witneſs the life of Chriſt in him by bringing it forth into the world, yet himſelf will preach Chriſt in him, and the Life of Chriſt in him, and the Spirit of Chriſt in him, and his body the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, &amp;c. Becauſe he finds theſe words in Scripture; but if any worſhip in that Temple ſo as to believe and obey unto life openly, that he cannot own without a meaning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof, and ſo he ſets the form to deny the Power, and Chriſts Words he wreſts to deny his coming; And how long this faith hath profeſſed him to come (and his Life and Glory at his coming) in its own carnal Comprehenſions, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may witneſs: but is never like to receive him in the ſame Life and Spirit and Power in which he ever appeared, and ſo to that generation is he ever to come, but never preſent, further then to make a cover for ſins paſt and preſent, and an encouragement for ſin to come; and thus the devou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>s the beſt of things into a lye in all that believes him, that he may keep Chriſt and the Soul from their preſent union, which he could not long do but by conſent of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there being that of God in every one which daily draws
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62425:15"/>
towards him, where it is not quenched by believing lies, whereby ſuch as receive not the Truth in the love of it comes to be damned, as it was in the dayes of old, and a ſtrait paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I have found into the way of Truth and life, which miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all his ſubtile pretences, and I have ſeen his words true who ſaith, Few there be that find it, the enemy being every way ready to meet them that ſeek with a ſhadow meaning, or ſome deceit to believe in ſtead of the ſubſtance, handling the Words of God deceitfully, uſing the gifts of God to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the life of the giver, and turning grace into lacivious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>And thus have I learned in the light of the world, that in my turning towards him at his reproof when I knew him not, and believing in his light whom I had not ſeen, I found that Faith given which did declare the righteouſneſſe of God in him, wherein he perfectly walked upon earth, both in doing and ſuffering, which being turned towards, I found the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation that God had ſent forth, through faith in his blood to declare his righteouſneſs for the remitting of my ſins paſt, that God might be juſt, who could not have paſt by my ſins paſt, had he not accepted his ſufferings, nor I have had liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from ſin paſt to have followed him, nor could I have been accepted therein, but in the faith and hope of the ſame righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; ſo God was full in juſtifying, and his forbearance magnified towards me therein, and in turning to this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of his declared in the light of faith and hope, my face was ſet towards righteouſneſſe in Chriſt Jeſus to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for life and ſalvation for time to come to walk in, and ſo being turned towards God, all my ſins paſt was behind me, and Gods righteouſneſs before me, and ſo from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth was I to be found in Gods righteouſneſs walking in a meaſure of it, and in the faith and hope of the fulneſſe of Chriſt and attainment of God for mine inheritance. And this great Redemption I found in Chriſt Jeſus at that day was in ſuch things as theſe following; As firſt his calling of me with his light, his holding forth to me his life and ſuffering, which was ſo holy that I could not but confeſſe to them, his turning me towards, the ſame in hope thereof by believing, his begetting a mind in me towards that ſame life, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62425:15"/>
of his light that way to lead me, and the ſetting of me free from the wrath of God for all my ſins of ignorance paſt, which elſe had laid upon me as a weight or chain, binding me that I could not have walked the way of his light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I do not ſay that if I turned to commit ſinne again, that that ſin was caſt behinde my back alſo, I learned otherwiſe, I found that ſinne then before my face greater then the reſt, and ſtood in my way to God, and ſtopt me from following his light or growing in his life that I could no way eſcape it but by repenting of it, and receiving the juſt ſentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in my ſelf, and bearing his indignation, till he that wounded me for it, healed me again, which I never found but as I turned from the evil with my whole heart, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the puniſhment till the advocate did ariſe to intercede, whoſe blood I had trampled on, and whoſe precious life I had pierced and his holy Spirit grieved, by turning away from his leadings.</p>
            <p>Nor do I ſay that all my ſinnes which formerly I had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, of which I had been convinced by the light of the <note place="margin">☜</note> world, when I was in the world before I believed it to be ſufficient, that they was wholly taken away as my ſins of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was, for this I found, that God in this was juſt and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, merciful in that he did not lay them all at once before me, leſt they ſhould have preſt me down that I could not have followed the light, nor gotten any ſtrength, but muſt needs have periſhed under them had he not ſpared. And juſt I have found him alſo; for as they were not committed all at once againſt the light of his Spirit, ſo he hath at one time or other viſited for them, and laid them before me, yet not all at once, nor no way ſo heavy as thoſe committed after I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and gave up my ſelf to follow the light, and yet to an account he hath brought me for them; and coming to feel the terrours of God, I have learned to fear, and love, and have found the ground, and riſe, and deceits of that Faith, that believes Chriſt to have taken away the ſins of believers paſt preſent, and to come, with which many at this day make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the witneſſe of God, and the juſt ſlain in them, and that Scripture I have learned without a meaning, if we ſin wilfully after we have received the knowledge of the Truth there remains no more ſacrifice for ſin, but a certain fearful
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62425:16"/>
looking for of judgement and fiery indignation to devour the adverſary, though none know how but he that comes to it, in the fulfilling, and then ſhall be ſeen he that's born of God ſins not, and he that believes is born of God, but he that ſins turns his back both on the Faith and Birth that's towards Chriſt, and becomes adverſe thereunto in his work what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſayes he believes, and this I have found an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth whatever men believe or imagine, that no longer then a man keeps his face towards the light of God, no longer is his ſins caſt behind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his back, whether they be ſins paſt, preſent, or to come, but if he turn from Gods righteouſneſs, his own ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities will riſe and mee him, both new and old, and in vain doth ſuch believe they are then blotted out of Gods fight, whoſe eye ſhews him his way in which he then walks, and condemns him for it in his own heart.</p>
            <p>Now was the ground and root of ſin removed ſo ſoon as my minde was turned by the light from ſin towards God, but the motions thereof I found, and the luſt ſeeking to go forth to its objects, to bring in to conceive ſinne again afreſh; that ground was but removed as I grew in Chriſt and he in me, and as I came to learn him that was in the beginning before ſin was, who was learned in faithful following &amp; ſerving of his Spirit, in watching, in faſtings, in prayers, and in all ſpiritual wreſtlings, as I came to be led into with the light, in which warfare I came to ſee the hardſhip of him that will be a ſouldier of Chriſt Jeſus, and the baptiſms into his death, the ſlothful ſervant and the faithful, and their reward, and the parables and figures of the Kingdom opened, as that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit grew in me which interprets the Scriptures in the life, and opens the ſealed myſteries thereof in their ſeaſon, as they come to be fulfilled; and ſo I came to the gift of the Scriptures by inſpiration, which onely profits to the perfecting of the man of God, which the man of this world not having learned, wreſts to his own deſtruction, getting the words of them in the earthly part, before they be fulfilled in his heart through the Spirit: and ſuch receive them not by inſpiration, nor the gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>And in this journey I have ſeen the ſlothful ſervant over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which he had once caſt behinde him, and never intended to joyn to again, of which the diligent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62425:16"/>
is kept free and I have ſeen the wages of each ſervant, according to his diligence in that which he hath of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted in him, and not by his own ſtrivings in the thoughts of himſelf, his worth, or wiſdom; and in diligent hearkening and obeying of the Spirit have I found the right f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rthfulneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, though getting knowledge be highly eſteemed with men, and I have found that as I have the Spirit mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in me to profit withal, ſo the times of my profiting is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his hand and my waitings upon him when he moves not is my reaſonable ſervice, and a profiting time to me as if he moved, though I ſee it not, and this I found a great croſſe to my haſty will, which indeed is the true worſhip in Spirit, which when I knew not this Spirit to hearken and bow to, and obey and obſerve in all things, as his will leads I worſhipped I knew not what, and my fear towards God then was taught by the precepts of men, and I was not taught of the Lord, not being born of that Spirit; and ſo all the children of the Lord are taught of the Lord; and as many as are led by the Spirit of God they are the Sons of God, theſe Scriptures I then could read and underſtand without meanings, not by that which my wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom taught me, but which the Holy Ghoſt taught me, and the Scriptures thus learned and received was no more a notion to be loſt, but a poſſeſſion, and I came to have an inheritance therein amongſt them that are ſanctified in all ages, and no ſubtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an could either ſteal them or change them, or any way beguile me of the truth of them by wreſting them nor take away my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort I had in them, my comfort and fellowſhip therein being in the ſame Spirit &amp; life that gave them forth, and the word of God thus grew and endureth for ever; and the Spirit of truth that leads into all truth endures for ever and the Seed of God is one therein to all generations, and that is one which perfects the Spirits of all juſt men, and God himſelf is Judge over all, and leader of all by his own begettings in all that enter into this reſt of the faithful, which remains to all his Children, out of which falſe Faiths and Diſobedience ſhuts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>And that which declares the righteouſneſſe of God for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes paſt, and for an inheritance againſt ſin for time to come, have I found to be Faith without falſhood,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62425:17"/>
which righteouſneſs though in the Faith and Hope beyond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, yet inherited but as the vertues that are in Chriſt Jeſus comes to be received in the life of them. And that faith which hath not that righteouſneſs for its ground and end and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and ſeveral meaſures of the growth of Chriſt for its life and increaſe, that I have found upon tryal to be a fained fancy after mans minde, and not after Gods meaſures: And he that ſaith he hath faith in God and is without the hope of this righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs for his inheritance. Or ſaith he, hath Chriſt further, then he hath his Vertues for his life and growth towards this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, when he comes to be weighed with Truth, will be found too light to ſtand in judgement or abide the fire, or to dwell with everlaſting burnings; the tryal of that Faith will leave him without faith, then ſhall it be read as it is written, <hi>When the Son of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> comes, ſhall he finde faith on tho earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Who they be that are under the Law, and who they be that have made void the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt themſelves, and who they be that are under Grace</head>
               <p>GRace reigns throvgh righteouſneſs, and the Law through Tranſgreſſion; and he that ſayes he is from under the Law, and the tranſgreſſor alive, he makes void the Law againſt himſelf, but is under it in the account of God.</p>
               <p>For the Seed or Image of God being fallen, the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor is above, to whom there is no Grace nor-Life promiſed, who hath no true obedience but for ſelf-ends; upon this is the Law added till the promiſed Seed ariſe: And a School maſter the Law is till it bring to Chriſt, who of the woman is made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, who takes upon him the Seed after the fleſh, the Soul to redeem from under the Tranſgreſſor, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Plant of God may grow, ſo who can witneſs the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Chaſtizings of the Law to bring him ſo low till he come under the Seed, ſo as the ſeed be ſet above the head of the Tranſgreſſor, and have bruiſed it, and have taken away the ſtrength of ſin, there the ſtrength of the Law is taken away al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: And as the Soul is raiſed up through the Law, the Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62425:17"/>
fulfilled by the ſeed through the Spirit, ſo it ariſes above the Law into the Kingdom of Grace, which reigns through Righteouſneſs, and not by making void the Law; for the Grace is to the Seed, and the Law to the Tranſgreſſour; and as theſe reign in the Creature, ſo is he under the law or under Grace, for the Law hath power over the man of ſin as long as he lives, then is the Seed of the Promiſe in bondage, but he being dead by which the ſeed is held captive the ſeed riſes under Grace, which as it rifes through the law fulfils it, and being fulfilled it loſes its ſtrength, as ſin dies, and ſo hath no more power, the Law being the ſtrength of ſin till it be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled by the ſeed through the Spirit; ſo he that is dead to ſin is free from ſin, and under Grace; And he that caſts off the Law while he is alive that ſins, makes void the Law againſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>So he thats under Grace is dead to ſin, and dead to the Law which is the ſtrength of ſin, and ſin hath no more domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over the ſoul, the power of it being ſubdued, which was the Law unfulfilled; but where the Law is made void, the ſtrength of ſin yet remains, and the Law will overtake them in the end.</p>
               <p>And he that learns this in the Death and Reſurrection, and eternal life, ſhall in this work learn what the Tranſgreſſion is, and how the law is added upon him, and how it is the ſtrength of ſin in him, but not in the ſeed, and what it is that makes the entrance through the Law, and how Grace comes to abound where ſin hath abounded, and to reign through Righteouſneſs unto eternal life.</p>
               <p>So where the Tranſgreſſor is ſlain, there the Law is at an end and fulfilled, and the natural Plant of God brings forth againſt which there is no law, but the law is againſt the man of ſin, and the man of ſin againſt the law as long as he lives, and power it will have over him, and one jot of it will not paſs away till it be fulfilled; And he that would caſt off the Law and make it void, is far from Grace, but in him that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fils the Law doth Grace and Truth abound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62425:18"/>
               <head>Of the Way of Life, from the Knowledge that devours the Life.</head>
               <p>WOuldeſt thou know the way of Life from that Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which devours the life; then be no longer as the wild Aſſes Colt, but take up the yoak of the Son, in whom thou ſayeſt thou believeſt, that the life of Faith thou may feel and know, for only in the obedience is the life made ſure to thee of what thou believeſt, and thereby is faith and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge made perfect.</p>
               <p>But untill thou attain power for obedience of Faith, thou art dead and knows but words, in which thy Faith ſtands without life which accompliſhes nothing, but will ariſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thee when thy time is out.</p>
               <p>Therefore in all thy ſeeking mind that which worketh in a lowly mind, calling thee into the Obedience of what is there made manifeſt in the begettings of the Father, and not in the conceivings of the Brain, but in the Son, For in the Brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Boaſter Rules who glories in the wiſdom of words, but not in the words of life; but in the Obedience of the Son is the Father known and glorified in ſuch as walk in the Spirit and not in the mind, whoſe praiſe is of God, and their lives hid with him from all knowledge but what is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Obedience of the Son: So from man you may learn the knowledge of words, but the knowledge of life is only begotten of God; ſo he that hath the Son hath life, not of the diſobedient Nature, for the only begotten of God is Conformable to him that begetteth him in all things through Obedience.</p>
               <p>So feeling thy meaſure of the begettings of God, in it be obedient, and ſeek not to be above it in any thing, leſt the enemy thereby get power in thee to puffe up thy mind in thy Knowledge above thy life, which devours the life.</p>
               <p>Therefore as thou feels Faith, Love, Meekneſſe, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Patience, or any Godlineſſe move in the Spirit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in become obedient with all diligence, and thereby ſhalt thou know the power thereof againſt all the contrary motions in thy fleſh, ſo ſhalt thou learn the ſalvation of Grace unto life
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62425:18"/>
eternal, which thou canſt never attain by talking or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way but in the Obedience thereof, ſo ſhalt thou not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the grace of God in vain, nor words without the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of life, whereby the living knowledge of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of godlineſs will daily increaſe.</p>
               <p>For by Obedience of the Spirit is the ſoul purified from its darkneſs and pollution, and made fit for the further manifeſtation of the hidden Myſtery, and the receiving the fulneſs thereof, and walking therein; And ſo by the holy Ghoſt thou ſhalt be able toconfeſs Jeſus Lord over all powers in heaven and in earth, the opener of all ſecrets, and only revealer of the Father who begetteth, by whom thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes wiſe in thy knowledge unto ſalvation, not unto vain babling, whoſe words ſhall riſe and Condemn them who glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therein.</p>
               <p>But thou, if in Spirit thou hearken diligently and obey, ſhalt know that he who ſometimes ſpoke by the Prophets doth now ſpeak by his Son, the everlaſting power of godlineſs, only begotten of the Father, and in all things like unto him, in whom he is made manifeſt; And the Prophets have Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of glory to come, but the Son declares the Father in the preſent life, according to the meaſure of him formed; and as he ariſes in fulneſs he opens the heavens and gives the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereinto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An opening of Light to all ſorts of Rulers and People that wait for the Kingdom of God, that you may not oppoſe him in his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, nor ſet up another to reign upon earth in his ſtead.</head>
               <p>DO you ſay you ſeek God you Rulers and People, will you ſeek his face upon earth? or would you ſee his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance to reign in righteouſneſs? or can you rejoyce to ſee him manifeſt in fleſh? or do you love his image who is the Fathers of Lights from whom you look for the Son from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? then be not carnally minded in your expectation, leaſt you know him not in his appearance who is a Spirit, and ſo, oppoſe him as your Fathers in the fleſh ever did, except
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62425:19"/>
you be born of the Spirit you cannot ſee the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p>The Father dwells in the light and changes not, and the Son is the light of the World in his own Image, by whom he changes all things that are out of him, and overturns ſhadows and cuſtoms, and makes the world new; and in Spirit and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is his Kingdom upon Earth, and the fleſh is the Vail with which he was ever hid from fleſh and bloud, but revealed in ſpirit to ſuch as deſired to know no man after the fleſh to ſet up or to worſhip; And no man could ever ſay that this Jeſus was Lord but by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>So with the light of the Spirit alone which ſees through the vail is Jeſus known to be Lord and King for ever, with which you may all ſee what you ſet up to be Lord and Ruler in your ſelves or over others. You that chuſe Rulers, Judges and Juſtices, Mayors and Conſtables, &amp;c. Do you ſee through the Vail to chuſe Jeſus in Spirit to Rule over you or over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Is that eye open which knows the Holy Ghoſt, &amp; what Veſſel is filled therewith, that you may chuſe him to Rule in his Kingdom? do you ſeek for that Spirit to chuſe withall by which alone Jeſus is known to be Lord? Then it is plain yon ſeek Gods Kingdom in the face of Jeſus Chriſt who is that ſpirit, which turning to, cauſes the vail to be taken away from all hearts, and will change you alſo into his image by that Spirit as ſaith the Scriptures. So there was none to be choſen for Judges Kings or Rulers in <hi>Iſraels</hi> Common-wealth but who had of this Spirit and Unction put upon them, and then the Lord Reigned over them in his Anointed, whether King, Prieſt or Prophet, man or woman; but when they chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Rulers like other Nations, then they rejected (not <hi>Samuel)</hi> but the Lord, that he ſhould not Reign over them. Now you that ſay you ſeek the Lord to Rule over you, and ſay thy Kingdom come, mind what you chuſe to rule in you or over you, &amp; with what ſpirit, leſt your practiſe oppoſe your prayers and make void your daily expectation; do you chuſe after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſh as other nations do, or do you chuſe after the holy Ghoſt? If you chuſe after the fleſh; then you ſet the vail betwixt you and the Lord, and Gods Kingdom and his image you cannot ſee, and ſo you reject the Lord as other nations do; but if you
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62425:19"/>
look through the Vail unto that which is within the Vail, then ſhall the vail be taken away from all your hearts, and you ſhall ſee him amongſt you whom you wait for, and him alone ſet up and worſhip, and chuſe him alone to reign over yon who is near you at hand to all that put not his day afar off.</p>
               <p>So if you make Rulers like all the Nations, then after the fleſh they that are rich, they that are proud, they that are full of earthly glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here is the earth ſet above, then the Vail is before your eye, and you ſee not the Lord that Spirit, nor do you ſet up Jeſus to be Lord by the Holy Ghoſt; but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that eye be open in you, that can ſee through the vail of earth, and all this deal of fleſh and darkneſs to that which is within the vail, even the holy One in his Temple, him to chuſe and ſet above in your mindes, then your eye ſhall ſee the Lords anointed, and the King in his glory, and he ſhall rule, whoſe right it is, in every heart, and your Governors ſhall be of your ſelves, and all violence ſhall ceaſe, and ſhakings of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Government being upon his ſhoulders, who is the Prince of all your peace, in the great and in the ſmall, who ſhall reign in righteouſneſs, and judge the people with equity for God, and not for rewards, to whoſe authority every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue confeſs for conſcience ſake, his name being written in every heart will then be read whoſe kingdom is everlaſting, and in ſpirit and power he reigns, and in ſpirit is worſhipped in heaven and in earth, who fills all things with the preſence of his Glory, and his kingdom is near to all that can believe, its within you, ſaith Chriſt, and he rules where he is not known (though not to ſalvation) who is made of the ſeed of <hi>David</hi> after the fleſh by the word of God to all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations a King for ever, according to promiſe, whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the eye which the god of this world hath blinded is put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting afar off, who ſees not the light of his glorious Goſpel though he be not afar off, but him in whom all things have life and being, either to ſalvation, or condemnation, and this is the condemnation, that light is come already into the world, which men who loves their evil deeds ſay is to come, and ſo looks for that withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who is a ſpirit within, and therein hath ever reigned more or leſſe, but now is ariſing to his day over all the world, whoſe ſound is gone out to the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62425:20"/>
ends of the earth, and his light ariſeth in every heart, to life or condemnation, and ſome it leads into reſt, and others it pricks to the heart, and they kick againſt it and will not have it to rule therein, and to this day he is rejected of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who is the firſt born unto God in Spirit bleſſed over all.</p>
               <p>And now all ſorts of people who in truth wait for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God upon earth, with that which in you is of him, you may all ſee (if you keep that eye ſingle) when he draws near who is born of the Spirit, and when he is put afar off in his Government here below, when you behold in any manner of Authority, ſuch a ſpirit as is for God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alone, looking to that of God in every man without reſpect of perſon or riches and with a ſingle eye ſeeks to find out where that meaſure of God is tranſgreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in any, or where it is oppreſſed by any, and with that meaſure of God in himſelf ſeeks to ſet judgement upon the head of the tranſgreſſor, and to ſet free the innocent principle of God in all, which will not lead any to evil, then is the judgement of God and for God, and that of God is ſet above in all, that's he that's born of God; here the kingdom of God is near, and as this increaſes ſo God draws near, and his Kingdome increaſes, and that of God in you all will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereto, and rejoyce thereat, which waits for him, and that which is upright in every heart ſhall ſay that is the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and in that Veſſel is God on his Throne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of that Spirit ſet up in Judgement, ſo is Jeſus Lord by the Holy Ghoſt, known and bowed to.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, in what place of authority ſoever it be, in which the Innocent comes for Judgement againſt the Oppreſſor who is too ſtrong for him, and ſo ſeeks to Juſtice to plead his Cauſe and to deliver the ſeed of God that is bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened; and when he comes his Cauſe is not heard, but is thruſt away (if not further enſnared) becauſe he cannot op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that of God in him more, either by bowing to ſomething of vain Cuſtoms or Worſhips never ſet up by God nor owned by his witneſs for Conſcience ſake; or elſe becauſe he cannot hire his judgement by feeding a covetous Spirit which is for Rewards, and not for God that he Judges, and ſo the innocent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62425:20"/>
ſoul is not relieved at this throne, but ſent away as an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, from that place where he ſhould be eaſed and juſtified with the judgement of a free ſpirit, for juſtice ſake, doth not that of God in you all teſtifie againſt this, that judgement is here turned backward in that veſſel, and that Jeſus is not Lord therein? ſo the innocent heart is ſadned, but not ſaved and the Kingdom of God put afar off, and the Scepter of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs not ſeen.</p>
               <p>Wherefore Rulers and People, who ſet up fleſh inſtead of the holy Spirit to rule over you, the wills of men, the pride and glory of this world, or any viſible thing here below born after the fleſh; ſee what you chuſe, and what you put afar off; and with that ſpirit you now chuſe you will never ſee the Kingdom of God, nor be able to ſay in truth that Jeſus is Lord; its by the ſpirit of holineſs, meekneſs, and true judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and works of righteouſneſs, that Jeſus is known to reign, and therein ſtands the ſight of his Kingdom, and Lordſhip, in every heart, in every Court, and in every place of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all generations, which you deny in chuſing the man of this world after the fleſh to rule in you, or over you therein; and yet you ſay you look for him, and thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come daily, but deny him in the ſimplicity of his low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit to rule for his own in all, as all your Rulers ever did, as you have read in words, and now may read in deeds, the world by wiſdom knows not God; ſo that ſpirit chuſes its own to rule, but cannot receive him whom you ſay you look for.</p>
               <p>And how ſhould any one who ſees the kingdom of God, and where the ſimplicity of Chriſt is above, own that kingdom, or worſhip that Spirit and not betray the ſimplicity of Chriſt, and give his honour to another. And if in the meekneſſe of mind you did but weigh this you could not think it ſo ſtrange why ſo many at this day (who have received the kingdom of God, in his lowly, juſt, and righteous ſpirit) chuſe rather to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death under that ſpirit of this world then to bow to worſhip it, or confeſs that due thereto which belongs onely to Jeſus the Lord, neither would you ſay it was obſtinacy or contempt of Authority rather to ſuffer by the will of man then to rob
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62425:21"/>
the Lord of his glory, and deny Chriſt in his kingly office, &amp; ſet up another in his place. And herein true wiſdom may ſee that in ſo doing we reſiſt not that power which is ordained of God, nor the perſon, but that ſpirit we teſtifie againſt by ſufferings under, which God never anointed for a Saviour, holding forth the anointing as we have received for a witneſs againſt him, in the ſpirit of meekneſs, confeſſing our King in whom we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive power to ſuffer; ſo to us he is come, and by the gift of the Holy Ghoſt we can ſay he is Lord; therefore to us there is but one Lord, though there be many ſo called, whether in heaven or in earth, yet have we but one in all, both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and him we know where ever he is by the gift of the Holy Ghoſt, and to him in ſpirit we confeſſe and bow, and the fruits of his ſpirit are manifeſt with the light of the world, teſtifying againſt all the works of darkneſs, in all the children of his kingdom. And to us he is born who is from above the Holy Child, wonderful in Councel and Strength, whoſe heavenly power and vertue takes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affections from all earthlyobjects and worſhip, whoſe name is Immanuel, and it is written in our hearts, and ſhed abroad into the world in our lives, and Chriſt Jeſus is the end of our converſation, him alone to put on, above all to preach by walking in him as we have received of that lively image of holineſs and truth, the anointed of God, and ſo we confeſs him before men, who is the right heir, in what veſſel ſoever he appears, and the praiſe we give to God where this treaſure is found in the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then veſſel, and the hope of all our glory is Chriſt within, and the increaſe of his government is Chriſt within, of which there is no end, and with that ſpirit is all righteouſneſs eſtabliſhed, the kingdom of God upon earth, and eternal life.</p>
               <p>And where this is not ſeen, choſen, and followed, there men rule in their own wills, and where mens perſons and riches is reſpected in chuſing ſuch, there the ſame is reſpected in judgement by ſuch, and the Law of God is perverted, and the ſword of Juſtice which ſhould defend the cauſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent is laid by, and the fiſt of wickedneſſe is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft up againſt that which is tender of God in every conſcience, and when this rules the righteous ſeed mourns in ſecret, but wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62425:21"/>
reigns openly; and this is and ever was the ſtate of the Kingdom of God and the Kingdoms of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the one rules in the Spirit of Holineſs, and the other exerciſe Lordſhip in their own wills, choſen and ſet up not by the Holy Ghoſt, as you may read in the Scriptures concerning <hi>Iſraels</hi> common wealth, who when they wanted the ruling of this ſpirit they ſold themſelves under their enemies, but when this was their Judge they had a Saviour choſen after the ſpirit, not after the fleſh, what ever was the veſſel, the Spirit was their Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> was a poor wandring Shepheard, yet in this Spirit a God to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and Saviour of <hi>Iſrael; Samuel</hi> a poor man who received no reward for judgment, and when they went about to chuſe another after the manner of other Nations they rejected God; who then gave them a King in his wrath; <hi>David</hi> a poor man not choſen by the outward appearance as man looks, but by the heart, by the direction of the Spirit, he was the Shepherd of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and his ſeed of the ſame Election hath the everlaſting Kingdom of promiſe to all generations. <hi>Eliſha</hi> a Plowman, yet by that Spirit was he the Chariots of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and horſmen thereof. <hi>Deborah</hi> a woman yet a Judge &amp; deliverer to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And too long would it be to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in all ages how he hath ſet up his throne and ſaved his people in this Election, not of wiſdom, riches or worldly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but the poor of this world, rich in faith, heirs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of promiſe, which you ſay you look for, but cannot ſee nor receive while you chuſe after the fleſh as the world hath ever done, who ſtill have bent all their wiſdom and Religion to keep the Heir out of his Kingdom, whom they have been looking for after the fleſh, but not believing in the light to give them a ſight through the vail to him that is born of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pirit have reſiſted the Holy One, and choſen the murtherer, as did your Fathers ſo do you alwayes reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, and as it was ſo it is, that which is born of the fleſh is fleſh, &amp; chuſes after the fleſh and worſhips after the fleſh, for it can ſee no further, it cannot ſee the Kingdom of God, and that which is born of the Spirit is Spirit, and chuſes after the ſpirit, and worſhips in ſpirit, and theſe are contrary Kingdoms, and he thats born after the fleſh perſecutes him thats born after
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62425:22"/>
the ſpirit, ever did and ever will do, for the Scripture cannot be broken, which hath ſo ſaid and is now fulfilled.</p>
               <p>And now you that are called Chriſtians, you read and Preach of this King Chriſt Jeſus and his Kingdom, what a One he ever hath been in his appearance upon Earth, by whom he hath been received and by whom rejected and after what manner he hath ever ſuffered, and by what power he hath reigned in all ages, and this you will confeſſe in words, but will you now receive him to reign in you? Or can you own his appearance where it is ſet up in others and not be offended therewith, is that eye open that knows him, or can you delight in him who was never like the world in his walkings? was not he ever poor as to this world, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rejected of the rich and learned? lowly, and rejected of Princes and them that was high? was not his work ever to change ſhadows, and forms, and Religious traditions ſet up in mens minds above the life of Truth and leadings of the ſpirit, and to ſet up ſpiritual worſhip and obedience in its place? And therefore by the builders ever rejected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and his new work was ever fooliſhneſs to the wiſe, wherefore he bare the reproach thereof with patience; was he not ever meek and innocent and harmleſs in his converſation towards all men as a Lamb indeed, ſeparate from ſinners in life; yet ſeeking them to ſave out of ſin with the daily gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up his life, &amp;c? So he was and ſo he hath ever appeared on earth, now can you receive him King as he was, you that wait for him? Or do you think he is changed? Is he now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come proud and lofty in fleſh after the world, cruel &amp; cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hard-hearted, ſubtle and crafty to deceive the ſimple, ſtrong and violent to trample on the helpleſs, doth the glory of his Scepter now ſtand in meats and drinks and fine apparel or great earthly poſſeſſions? doth he now come to take up his abode and delight in theſe things, who ever hath come to take the minds of his people out of theſe things up into the heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treaſure? doth he now delight in earthly glory, ſtrife and exaltation? Is the weapons of his warfare now become carnal wherewith he over comes his enemies? doth he now come with haling and beating, whips and priſons and cruel tortures to take the Kingdom of peace, who hath ſuffered ſuch things
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62425:22"/>
formerly from the world himſelf, &amp; will he now turn oppreſſor of that which is tender in Conſcience, and grind the face of the poor, or pervert the Judgment of the needy? Should he now be ſeen in works of this nature, were this to appear the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation as he is promiſed? Sure the vail is thick over that heart who ſees not that this is not his Kingdom, Power nor Glory, nor his image who is the ſame yeſterday to day and for ever. Yet is this nature above in many, and choſen to Rule over many who ſay they wait for his Kingdom, that eye being darkned with the love of the world which ſhould give the true ſight of his coming, the carnal mind thinks God to be like himſelf; But did you but honeſtly look into your own hearts, with that eye which puts a difference between things that differ in your ſelves, to know each motion of each Spirit, and each power, and the end and nature of its working, the earthly and the heavenly, you would ſoon be able to Judge of theſe two which ſo far differ in their fruits, and are ſo contrary in all things, and to own the right heir in his Kingdom: But while you ſuffer the god of this world to keep his Throne in your hearts, by letting him captivate your minds and affections into earthly delighrs, it is not like he will ſuffer you to chuſe aright, nor receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to reign in you or over you; the eye of the mind being blinded therewith, the light of the Goſpel cannot ſhine into the heart by which you ſhould chuſe, and which gives the knowledge of God in the face of Jeſus, nor that treaſure be ſeen or received in the earthen veſſel, as King either in your ſelves or others; but the wiſe in heart knows what they wait for, and when they ſee him they rejoyce with the joy of his Kingdom which conſiſts not in carnal things, nor comes with outward obſervations, but whoſe coming is within, and whoſe Kingdom conſiſts in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt, bleſſed be our King for ever, and bleſſed are they who put not his Kingdom afar off..</p>
               <p>And therefore you Rulers and People of all ſorts high and low, this word is to you, and this day is to you the day of the Lord, ariſe and receive your King into his Kingdom, that he may receive you and eſtabliſh you therein; the Lord it at hand, he is near to all that call up on him in truth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62425:23"/>
To you Princes, Judges, Juſtices Mayors and Conſtables &amp; all ſorts of Rulers who are in the place to Govern, the Lord is at hand, he is near you all, the Kingdom of God is within you, the Principle of God is within you, with which (if you mind it) he will break the yoak of the oppreſſor within you and without you by the ſword of Juſtice, thats his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom upon earth, put it not afar off, let it ariſe in your hearts, ſet it up above the will of man, let it ſhine in your hearts, let it ſpeak in your Courts, that which is of God in you all, which Judges juſtly and with equity; lay by your will, your pride, your covetouſneſs, and all thats above that Spirit of meekneſs in your minds, and make room in your hearts for the Holy Ghoſt, that thereby Jeſus may be Lord in you and over others, that you may. know him to whom Judgment belongs, to be in you; you need not ſay who ſhall aſcend into heaven to bring down Chriſt from above, or who ſhall deſcend into the deep to bring up Chriſt again from the dead, for he is nigh you, and you may feel his witneſs in Spirit, and his Word is in your hearts, the Word of Faith, the Word of Righteouſneſs, that therewith you may all know him, who ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty, to Judge among the Gods, who Judgeth not unjuſtly, nor accepteth the perſon of the wicked, but that with him you may deliver the Poor and Fatherleſs, and Judge the cauſe of the ſtranger, wherein they are oppreſſed, that his Kingdom, and thats the Word of Faith and the Word of Righteouſneſs that leads to it.</p>
               <p>And if this be ſet up in your own hearts to love it more then gifts and rewards, perſons or earthly glory, then is the Lord near you, and his Kingdom is above the earth in you, and your work will be to ſet it above the earth in others, and ſo the Kingdom of your Father who begets this in your hearts his Kingdom comes, as his Will is done upon earth as it is in Heaven, where all obey him, there is the Kingdom his, the Power is his by which you Judge, and the glory is his of your Righteous Judgment, now and for ever if you therein abide: And thus ſhall you be of the obedient Children to that of your Father in you begotten, who ſay and do, who pray and practiſe, and not like the Scribes and Phariſees and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62425:23"/>
Lawyers, who ſaid and did not, who made long prayers, but devoured the poor and needy, and judged not the cauſe of the ſtranger, but laid heavy burthens upon others, and bowed not thereto themſelves, who could not believe in the light, nor receive Chriſt within them, though he told them the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God was within them, and his word had no place in them, who was filled with pride and wilfulneſs; ſo they had loſt the key of knowledge, the key of <hi>David,</hi> to open to them the way into the anointing, whereby to know <hi>Davids</hi> Lord to reign in Spirit, which hath the promiſe of <hi>Davids</hi> Throne for ever: So when they loſt this the kingdom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Prieſthood alſo; and he ſet up his ſign to the Gentiles, preaching the kingdom of God to rhem that were afar off, and they that were not a people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame to the kingdom of his anointing, and that great myſtery that had been hid from ages was opened thereby to the Gentiles, which was Chriſt in them, the hope of Glory, and Kingdom of the Father.</p>
               <p>And now you that are called Chriſtians, and are making great Declarations, what a glorious Kingdom the Kingdom of Chriſt will be at his coming, and what holineſs and righteous Government, and many high things and great glory you look for, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But above all the reſt, how are you eſtranged, who are gone out again from the anointing to look for this without you, while you reject it within you? Was Chriſt within them, that great myſtery that had been hid from ages, which by the hearing of faith was opened to the Gentiles, and was the hope of Glory to them (even Chriſt within them, whom the Apoſtles preached, warning every man, and teaching every man that they might preſent every one perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, the hope of Glory within them, which Faith the Jews not receiving, loſt their King and Kingdom? And is your hopes without you, as the Jews was? Is that the Hope the Apoſtles preached to the Gentiles, or that which enters within the vail? Is there not a vail drawn over your hearts again, whilſt you read this in Scriptures? And have not you loſt the key of knowledge, who are gone out from the anointing in your hopes? Have you not loſt the key of <hi>David,</hi> which ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62425:24"/>
let you ſee <hi>Davids</hi> Lord, in which the kingdom of God is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed for ever? Did God ſwear this to <hi>David</hi> after the fleſh, or to <hi>Abraham</hi> after the fleſh, or to any after the fleſh? Then how is his kingdom everlaſting? Or why did he ſay, the fleſh profits nothing? And why did the Apoſtle ſay, they deſired henceforth to know no man after the fleſh, no not Chriſt himſelf? Fleſh and blood paſſeth away, but this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is everlaſting; ſo him whom the Apoſtles preached in Spirit by the receiving of the Holy Ghoſt, wherein they were to grow up to his age, and ſtature, and appearance, him you reject in ſpirit to be the hope of your glory and kingdom and wait for a government after the fleſh, and fo ſhut up the great myſtery of godlineſs which was opened, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom againſt your ſelves which myſtery is not after the fleſh, but God manifeſt in fleſh, Chriſt within the hope of Glory, and this myſtery was ever ſhut with carnal expectations, but opened in the Spirit, as it was, ſo it is, who denyes the Spirit to be Lord ſhuts up the kingdom.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ariſe out of the fleſh you Rulers and People, and receive your King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> long hath he been rejected and thruſt out of the Throne of Judgement, for which you have no Peace nor Eſtabliſhment; why will you not turn to him who calls you in Spirit, what a ſhame is this, that you are called Chriſtians, and know not your anointing Chriſt in you? What, Chriſtians and without Chriſt, Chriſt not come? What do you rule withal, and diſcern with, and judge with? Is not all that reprobate, who knows not Chriſt in you? But if you know a juſt, a holy, a righteous principle of Spirit in you that is of Chriſt, ſet it up, and you ſet up Chriſt, bow to the Holy Ghoſt and you worſhip in Spirit and thereby you ſhall ſay that Jeſus is Lord, ſet up his light in your hearts and his day will ariſe to you all. for there muſt the day dawn and the day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts, which will give the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God near you, and true judgement near you, and that which rules over ſpiritual wickedneſs near you, which all muſt bow to who receives the kingdom of God, honour God in your hearts, ſet him up in your hearts, let him be Judge in your hearts, and firſt receive his Light and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62425:24"/>
there, before you paſs judgement upon others, leaſt you in judging others before men condemn your ſelves before God; <hi>David</hi> had little thought he had done that, when he ſaid, he that had taken his neighbours lamb ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urely dye; and you may ſoon do the like if you go out from the Spirit and judge before you receive judgement in your own hearts, and ſee all be clean there firſt, then is your Scepter eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, and your judgement in truth, which is the Scepter of the Throne of <hi>David</hi> in Spirit, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned <hi>David</hi> in fleſh, and will condemn you in the fleſh if you ſin againſt it; and that is his kingdom, and he is King for ever, who in Spirit condemns ſin in the fleſh, and for this end is he manifeſt, that the righteouſueſs of the Law may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in all who walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit, which comes in his Name, who went away after the fleſh that the kingdom might come. And if you receive your authority and judgement in this right principle of God, it will judge for God in all yoor ſelves, and others, and it will fit you to be mediators betwixt the Offender and Sufferer in all, and you will ſee what it is which tranſgreſſeth, and what is tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the nature of every offence to paſs an equal judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accordingly, and this is of God, and he loves it, and where that of God is preſſed, not to clear the oppreſſor, but to judge the oppreſſor, and ſet that of God which is innocent free; and here with that of God in your ſelves you judge for that of God in all, and ſet that of God above the oppreſſor in all, which oppreſſor is not of God in you nor in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers, but is to be judged, and for the Law and for the Sword, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that of God, the Law is not; and here is Gods king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom already near, and not afar off, where God is all in all and the righteous reigns, and the power that is ordained of God, the ſoul is ſubject to for conſcience ſake towards God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and eaeth, and that of God in every conſcience ſhall anſwer to your Judgement and Authority, and God ſhall ſet you up therewith as a terrour in every heart above the evil doer, the murtherer and traytor, and the Arrows of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſhall ſtick in the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of all that ſeek to undermine this Government, for the kingdom of God it is, in which he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62425:25"/>
Rules, who cannot forget himſelf, nor hath this kingdome been taken from any who once received it thus, till they go out of it themſelves, by ſuffering or ſetting up another to rule above that meaſure of this juſt and innocent principle of God.</p>
               <p>And if you receive this kingdom from heaven in love of it, then ſhall you receive your judgement from heaven alſo, and your Law-to judge by, and God ſhall make you rich towards him in righteous judgement, and towards his People, and a diſcerning ſpirit will he give you in this anointing to know hard matters that are hid from fleſh and blood, which you ſhall receive in ſecret, and bring forth openly, and all ſhall hear and fear, and praiſe the Lord for you; and you ſhall no more go to the Heathen to learn judgment whom the Lord hath removed far from him, nor ſhall you uphold thoſe Laws by which the ſervants of God hath ſuffered formerly in the times of Popery, nor ſhall the Statutes of <hi>Omri</hi> be kept and obſerved, nor follow the wayes of the houſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> for you have ſeen what God hath done concerning them, that you may fear to follow them: But you ſhall have your Laws from the Law-giver Chriſt Jeſus, and your judgement from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, whoſe Miniſters then you are, to whoſe ſword that of God in every Conſcience ſhall anſwer, which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in every heart, and which every heart ſhall fear to offend, when they hear that the Lord hath raiſed him up Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellours as at the beginning, and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſhall hear and fear, and come to you to learn Judgement, and righteouſneſs ſhall ariſe from amongſt you to the ends of the earth, &amp; the break of Gods day ſhall be with you firſt, as to you it is firſt tendred if you be not found unworthy to receive him, and he ſhall make you as a head in Counſel, and the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn of all Nations unto God ſhall you be if you receive him; wherein the bleſſing of God is bound up by an oath, and his ſtrength upon earth to all generations.</p>
               <p>And this is the love of God to you all once more, The Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of theſe Nations, from the higheſt to the loweſt, that love might open your hearts that the earth hath ſhut and ſealed, that you might come to a feeling of your everlaſting
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62425:25"/>
eſtabliſhment, and that your fears may ceaſe in an endleſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nion betwixt Chriſt your King and your own ſouls, to the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead of all your enemies, and eternal praiſes lift up to him indeed, who hath ſcattered your enemies many a time for you, and all their dark plots brought to light, that you may love the light wherein is your ſalvation, and not plot in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt his innocent ones, as your enemies do, but with hearts open and naked receive the truth, which condemns all the deeds of darkneſſe in you and in them, leaſt he bring your Plots and ſecret Counſels againſt the innocent upon your heads, as he hath often done to your enemies, for he will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the poor, though long he ſuffer with them and in them; and this is now ſeen concerning you, as was formerly ſeen concerning them, of which they were warned in words, and witneſſed againſt in ſufferings long before it came, who are now broken as a Potters veſſel, and cannot be made whole, but what ever they do, breaks them more. And now are you warned and invited in love, who ſees before you this day what God hath done concerning them, and ſuffered concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you.</p>
               <p>And I am bold in the love of God to ſend this to you all wherein there is a Seed of God, and I know there is that of God in you which will anſwer to the truth of this; and the Scriptures witneſſe with me alſo, ſo I am not alone, but by two infalible witneſſes every word is eſtabliſhed, either to life or condemnation; and my prayers to God is and ſhall be, as long as this of God in me hath breathings, That you may receive the Kingdom of God which is near you, through that ſpiritual Light and Key that opens the door of your entrance thereinto, that you may come to be eſtabliſhed in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God and not of man, and that you may not reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt, as hitherto you have (many of you) done, nor kick againſt that which pricks you at your hearts when you are told hereof, leaſt you be broken in the end, ſo as you can never be healed, which is near at hand to be broken or eſtabliſhed, as you receive God or refuſe him, who hath long waited upon you that now are, and with much patience is he finiſhing as large a Teſtimony of his ſuffering and forbearance among
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62425:26"/>
you, as ever was ſince the world began, though it be little ſeen where the light is rejected, which the longing of my Soul is, may be for the leading to Repentance, that you may be eſtabliſhed after all this ſhakings in that which cannot be ſhaken, otherwiſe the moſt miſerable Wo that ever wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will come upon you, your Profeſſion of Chriſt being the greateſt that ever was ſince the beginning; And his Oppreſſion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, under which he ſuffers in all places of the Nations for a teſtimony that the Kingdom is near you, whether you will receive him or refuſe him, whoſe life in meaſure is now manifeſt in mortal fleſh, and the light thereof ariſeth in every Conſcience to lead or condemne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Candle lighted, to give the ſight of the good Old Way of God at his Coming from the wayes that now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnares the ſimple.</head>
               <p>A Voice in the Wilderneſſe cryes aloud to all you who are talking of the Lords coming, prepare his way, make his paths ſtrait, make way for the Juſt to come to Judgment, make him way in your ſtreets, he comes not in a corner, nor is he kept in the ſecret chambers, but openly in the ſtreets of the great Cities, where iniquity is committed openly, whoſe Cry hath gone up before the Lord, and he comes to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo indeed as the Cry hath been: And behold here is no room for the feet of his Servants to paſſe, in whom he comes; The antient paths of Peace are broken up, the Sea hath broken its Banks, it rages and ſwells exceedingly, and the good old Wayes are grown like a Wilderneſſe, they are filled with heaps of Rubbiſh, ſo that the Stranger cannot paſſe, who hath no habitation in the Earth; our ſtreets are become as <hi>Sodom</hi> which God overthrew, who can ſee and not lament? How are the paths of the Juſt devoured? How is Bryars and Thornes grown over the way of the Righteous, which takes hold of the upright what way ſoever he turn, if he come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin? So the Innocent paſſe if he come in the Name of the Lord: All hath freedom but the Heir, and ſuch
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62425:26"/>
as he ſends before his face to prepare his Way; Swearers, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, Drunkards, and all deceitful workers are become Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, have free paſſage, and every one brings forth without fear; but he that departs from Iniquity, and teſtifies againſt it, is beſet about with them all, as a Sheep in the bryars, what way ſoever he turns, his bonds are increaſed. How is true Judgment driven into a corner, and Wickedneſſe come into the ſtreets, which riſes up without fear againſt him that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it? for Violence hath got into the Seat of Equity, and hath framed miſchief by a Law, and hath turned Judgment backwards.</p>
               <p>Should not Truth have its way amongſt you Profeſſors, and righteous Judgment paſſe upon its Enemies where they are found, and plead its own cauſe againſt Iniquity? But he that letteth ſtands in the way with his Weapons to devour him that is more Righteous then himſelf, and no man is able to reſtore to the upright his path; Or can he redeem his own way, but through blood? Shall he condemn Iniquity, and not be a prey? Or ſhall he reprove ſin in the Gate, and not be taken in their Dragg? And when the Innocent is caught in this Net, to whom ſhall he cry for relief and not increaſe his bonds? Or who will plead his Innocent Cauſe, and not betray him? If he would appeal to Iuſtice, he cannot come at it, nor doth Iudgment ſit in the Gate? Is there help in the Houſe of the King, or will the Houſe of the Prieſt plead his Right? Or to whom may he commit himſelf with ſafety, whoſe Life and Faith is held in a pure Conſcience? Or in what Court can he appear without offence? Are not Snares laid in lower places, and on the Mountains a Net ſpread? And do not theſe daily catch men? Search if there be a man left that is valiant for Truth upon Earth, who for fear or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour will not wink at Oppreſſion, or that dare faithfully ſtand by him that comes in the Name of the Lord to reprove ſin openly: who is he that hath not laid Riches, or Honour, or ſome piece of Earth in his own way to ſtop his feet from the path of uprightneſſe, and ſo is every mans Arm become too ſhort to relieve the Oppreſſed, or to open the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Innocent may ſerve his Maker without fear? Or the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62425:27"/>
Juſt to proclaim the Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of God without danger, in the way that God ſhall chuſe, and not man; Or for Judgment to come forth into the open places where wickeneſſe is moſt acted: Or for the lively witneſſe of the Lamb to ariſe againſt his enemy in the good old way that he hath choſen to all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations?</p>
               <p>Ah! how is the Antient paths forſaken of men? How have you left the good old Way of God, and choſen wayes of your own ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt your own ſouls? How long will it be ere you try your wayes with the truth, that you may returne to him who is come to require the Paths of judgment and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and truth, that the meek may poſſeſſe his Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of old, and that God may walk in his own ſeed as he hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them, and walk in them, who comes as the lightning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold you who are crying againſt new wayes, you ſay it was never well ſince there was ſo many new wayes, you are the men, and your wayes are the thing you complain of, and why there is ſo many of your wayes, is becauſe <hi>Babel</hi> is confounded, and many Heads and Horns are lifted up to fulfil that number, as is written of them to withſtand the way of the Lamb, and to fight againſt Gods appearance in his heritage; who all are ſet againſt the way of God as at this day, which is but one to all generations: was not this his way of Old which is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and which is become ſo odious in your eyes? Was not this of old the pure path, which you now ſay breaks your peace? Search the Scriptures which teſtifie of God and his way in his ſervants of old, and how he then paſſed in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ones, choſen veſſels for himſelf, to make his power known againſt oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, as you may read in Scriptures, trace the ſteps of his ſervants in whom he walked, and ſee how far you have erred at this day.</p>
               <p>Was not this his way in <hi>Jeremiah?</hi> Who led him into the gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and through the ſtreets thereof, through him declaring againſt ſin there abounding, and to pronounce judgments to follow? did not he lead him into their Temple, and therein told them who went thither to worſhip that they truſted in a Lye, who cryed the Temple of the Lord, but had
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62425:27"/>
made it a Den of Thieves by their wicked wayes? D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not he lead him down to the houſe of the King, and there told him, That if he would not amend his wayes his houſe ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a deſolation? And which of the falſe Prophets did he not reprove openly by him? Was not this his way then? And what became of them that would have ſlopt him? Did not he ſpeak words in <hi>Amos</hi> againſt the Wickedneſſe of their King, Prieſts and Worſhips, that the Land was not able to bear? Did not he lead <hi>Jona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> through the ſtreets of <hi>Nineveh?</hi> And in which of the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s did not he thus walk in, and ſome received him in his way, and turned from their own wayes and found Mercy; and the reſt that rejected him were deſtroyed in their own wayes in which they bleſſed themſelves as at this day? Now read theſe, and read what you now op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in your Streets and Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple-houſes, and Markets, and let that of God in you be judge if you be not of ſuch as now ſay, Depart from us we will have none of thy wayes? Alſo ſearch your Goſpel if you can receive his way therein which changes not. Did not he come in Chriſt, and in his Apoſtles as a wandere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to and fro, without a certain dwelling place, to Preach Repentance and amendment of life, and the light of the world, from City to Village, from place to place, which way you now call Vagabonds? And did not he enter their Temples and Synagogues, Schools and Markets, and all their places of Worſhip and concourſe, where ſin or falſe Worſhip was acted, and there Diſputed and teſtified againſt their whole way, and called them to the way of God, and this was his manner of walking in them, even in times of their Worſhips, and in the greateſt Aſſembly of Meetings and Markets, which to you is become as gall and wormwood, and you call it Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance and Peace-breaking.</p>
               <p>Was not this his way in ſuch as knew their bodies to be his Temples, and in whom he walked and ſpoke the words of Life, and Judgment, and Truth, his way by which he overturned the World, leaving all without excuſe againſt the day of wrath which was to follow where he was rejected, his way by which he called many thouſands out of falſe Worſhips in which they were ſetled (as you are) and their Souls deceived, but this
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62425:28"/>
was his way to Salvation, which was not their way (as he hath ſaid, my wayes are not your wayes) yet was there no other way f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r them to be ſaved, which is the ſame at this day to all that receive his coming, and to all that reſiſt the Holy Spirit in his Temples; as did your fathers, ſo do you ſaith <hi>Stephen</hi> to ſuch as worſhipped God in outward obſervations, but denied his way and worſhip in Temples made without hands: theſe reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt, reſiſted the way of God, as do you. Read and conſider, <hi>Steven</hi> was full of God, the Spirit ſpake in him, they reſiſted him, they called him a Blaſphemer, they ſtoned him by a Law: here was Gods way, and their way, now try your wayes whoſe work is to reſiſt the Spirit and Light within, which hath filled the hearts and mouths of his ſervants to cry againſt ſin. Mind what you r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſiſt.</p>
               <p>Had not God come in this his own Way to ſeek and to ſave by his appearance in ſuch veſſels as he had prepared of old for that end (whom in time he filled with himſelf, as they ſtood in need, in all conditions to paſs with him through all hardſhips and crooked wayes of the wicked world, from place to place ſeeking a ſeed to himſelf) what had become of the Saints of old, which was covered with darkneſſe, till he came thus to appear to them holding forth his light, and his life and glory in veſſels prepared, to ſhew forth his vertues and the riches of his grace, not only in declaring in words, but alſo in power, to ſuffer for his Name long and hard Tryals, with much patience and meekneſſe, in all which they became ſigns to the world, and lively witneſſes of God to his own in every Conſcience, whereby the Seed of God in many, gathered ſtrength to ariſe out of darkneſſe and come to judgement, and by their ſufferings waxed confident in the Faith, that it was the eternal God that they had ſeen preached; and that was in them who thus ſuffered, and did not receive their words as the words of men, but of God, who was with them and in them in all. And this his way was not only to receive ſuch as came to him, but with danger of life went in to their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies and publick places, to bring them out of the claws of the Devil, who beat ſome in their Synagogues, haled ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Rulers, caſt ſome into Priſon; who ſuffered great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62425:28"/>
to bring ſouls from under the dark power, and in all this God was afflicted with them, and by his own Spirit brought them out, and this was his way of ranſoming and redeeming, and of bringing to <hi>Zion</hi> as you may read of old. And thus by his Spirit and by his working in them did he work wonders and ſigns, and was a witneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the whole body of ſin, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturning falſe wayes and worſhips by a way they knew not: nor did the world know it was he, until he had brought to paſſe his work upon them, having thus gathered out his Seed from amongſt them, who then ſought to ſtop his way, as you do at this day. And what was their end?</p>
               <p>And in this way was the Churches of Chriſt gathered even blood, and ſufferings, and tumults, and beatings, and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and whippings, and all manner of cruel uſage, fighting with beaſts after the manner of men; and by the patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt in them, were many recovered out of the ſnares of the Devil, which had he not ſought them in this way, they had lived and died in blindneſſe. And this was the way in which God gathered the Churches (which you who oppoſe this way would imitate) and in this way was the miſtery of Godlineſſe, and the miſtery of iniquity revealed, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt known upon earth; and in this way came the Scriptures of the Apoſtles and Prophets, of which you talk, and would turn to oppoſe this way; like them who read his coming in the Prophets, and would have ſtopt his coming in Chriſt and the Apoſtles, ſo do you ever reſiſt the way of the Holy One, and yet in words you pray for his coming, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving erred in your hearts from that light which ſhould give the knowledg of him, you know not his wayes, but have in your imaginations ſet a new way for his appearance, every one in his own form, but all think you are doing him ſervice, to ſtop his old way by force.</p>
               <p>Ah fooliſh people (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull of wit) will you call on him to come to judgment, and ſtop his way with cruelty? Is not the day of the Lord darkneſſe to you who deny the light? Gods wayes are not yours, nor his thoughts yours, who are vain therein; will you hedg up his way againſt him? will you ſet B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iars and Thorns before him? and ſhall not the light
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62425:29"/>
of <hi>Iſrael</hi> kindle a fire amongſt you? ſhall not he go through and tread you down, and with your own tear you as a Lion from whom none ſhall deliver?</p>
               <p>Was it not thus with <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they builded Temples and increaſed their Altars, and multiplied their Sacrifices? &amp; what was the end, was it not all to ſin? for thereby they ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves againſt the way of the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in his Prophets, and bleſſed themſelves in their worſhips, &amp; ſaid no evil ſhould come upon them, for they made many prayers, but their hands were full of blood, for the beſt of them was become as a Bryar in the way of the Innocent, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he moſt upright as a Thorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedg in the way of his ſervants, in whon he appeared againſt their back-ſliding evils and falſe worſhips, but they were not ſo to their own Teachers, for them they fed fat, and gave gifts, rewards, and hire to them; ſo having got Prophets of their own in their way, then they joyned together, and one cryed peace to another, and when God came to break that peace in his way, and to tell them it was not his peace, then they all joyned to hedge him out, and made a wall againſt him of their own righteouſneſſe, which they daubed up with their increaſe of Sacrifices and falſe worſhips, ſo they ſaid they were innocent people; ſaid ſo, and Prieſt, and Prophets, and Rulers ſaid ſo, for they had trimed their own ways, ſo they ſaid they ſhould have peace, and he that told them truth then became their troubler. So having covered themſelves with this garment, they could ſhed innocent blood boldly, which was found in the Skirts thereof not by ſecret ſearch; and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of all this? did their own wayes ſave them in the end? did not innocent blood out-cry the multitude of their Altars, till there was no remedy? So he became their enemy whom they called their Redeemer.</p>
               <p>So now read your wayes at this day and meaſure them in Truth, and ſee what it is you are hedging our, who it is, and what is his meſſage againſt, and what is his manner of coming, and our manner of oppoſing, that ſo, if it were poſſible, you might come to ſee a glimps of the old way, and of your own works; is it not he that comes to cry out againſt that which is wicked in your ſtreets, and falſe in your worſhips, that's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62425:29"/>
your enemy, and breaks your peace, whom your hedge cannot ſtop nor your wall keep out? how many bryars and Thorns are ſet againſt him at this day to take hold of him if he do but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his mouth in your ſtreets, what Laws new and old the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is to make him an offender for a word in your Temples; how is he beat in your Synagogues, haled before Rulers and caſt into Priſons? how is the Scriptures fulfilled upon you, and his witneſs doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt you manifold over, above all your forefathers of whom you read, and yet you ſay you are innocent, you are no perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors but for liberty of Conſcience, they were perſecutors that ſo uſed him in the Prophets and in the Apoſtles, and in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes that ſo uſed Martyrs, &amp;c. but cannot ſee your work of the ſame nature, which <hi>Queen Maries</hi> Laws are far too ſhort for you to accompliſh, but with many additions thereto are you in much fury driving on to deſtruction, yet having trimed your own way, ſay you, we are Chriſtians and have a Goſpel Miniſtry of godly men, &amp;c. But what Chriſtians? did ever Chriſtians count it a breach of their Peace to reprove ſin in the Gate or where ever it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? did Chriſtians ever caſt into priſon, or count it diſorder to diſpute in their Synagogues in the time of their worſhip? did they ever make a Law to whip ſtrangers who asks them nought, or to force people to ſwear againſt the conſcience? and many ſuch things are now done which in the time of the Apoſtles the heathen came far ſhort of, which now is filling up all againſt him whoſe coming is ever as a ſtranger in the earth, and what hedgings here is at this day to keep him out from his own is plainly to be ſeen, and that he ſhould not have liberty to ſeek up his loſt ones in high-wayes and hedges, Markets and Steeple-houſes; how have you heightned your walls higher then your fore-fathers? and what daubing is at this day againſt the way of God, from which your own wayes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave you? for the way of God is perfect and will endure to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Generations, wherein the upright walks and ſinners falls in oppoſition thereto.</p>
               <p>But how ſhould you know his way who denies his light within, ſeeing they that rebell againſt the light never knew the pathes thereof; you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they who have erred in your hearts and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have not known his wayes, and how ſhould you have peace or enter into his reſt, for you that denies his light and reſiſts his Spirit
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62425:30"/>
in your hearts muſt needs be offended at his coming in your ſtreets, ſo you have ſet your ſelves againſt him, and he hath ſet himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you as at this day, and therefore it is not with you now as it was when you were in the work of making him way to walk in tender conſciences, and you will find him ariſe more to croſs your wayes as you ſeek to ſtop his way, you have begun to walk contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him, and he is beginning to walk contrary to you, and unto you is he become an enemy; ſo take heed what you do, for till you return will he watch over you for evil and not for good, and the more you trim your own wayes to withſtand his way, the more will he diſcover the blood of the innocent in your skirts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun, till all may ſee you are no Chriſtians, nor what you Profeſs, but open enemies to God and his people, and your hands full of blood; Wherefore be not raſh, you heady people, you that are but looking for his coming i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> outward obſervations, are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt your ſelves that his way you have not yet learned, though you have read of it, yet you know it not, and will you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him a way, and call it his way, and will he own it, who comes a way you have not known nor can believe if you be told it? it would be your wiſdom to ſtand ſtill every one and ceaſe from your own wayes, and wait in the light, which only gives the knowledge of him and his way, which light ſhines in the heart as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and the Kingdom of God is within you, and he whom you oppoſe is a Spirit, and comes a ſpiritual way to cut down ſpiritual wickedneſs; ſo to the Spirit of light turn that you may ſee to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet him in his own way, and not to ſet your way to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him, that he ſhould not break you to pieces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The living God glorified in his Temple, the true Worſhippe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth.</head>
               <p>NOw glory to God in Heaven, and the thouſands of his Saints doth confeſs him upon earth, who bear his Name and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the world, who have ſtill put his coming afar off, who have not that which they profeſs in them, but tell of great things which they have not, who are without God in ſpirit, and his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in Spirit, ſuch as Chriſt ſaid worſhipped they knew not what, and ſuch now worſhip they know not what, who worſhip that they have not, and profeſs him they poſſeſs not, without God in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62425:30"/>
world, in whoſe heart there is not God, who are not the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the living God, but to this day worſhip in Temples made with hands, as thoſe who reſiſted the Holy Ghoſt ever did, and how ſhould ſuch be holy veſſels, holy men and women? what ſhould ſanctifie where God is not, and what ſhould lead where the ſpirit is not, but the blind eye that leads into the ditch? and what is like to govern where God is not in his throne in the heart, how can ſuch but be filled with unrighteouſneſs who retain not God in their knowledge? ſo it is not ſtrange to the children of light who with the eye of God are guided to ſee the whole world lie in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and to ſee ſuch thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> acted againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God in his Temples now, by ſuch as are without God as ever was, ſo the Scriptures are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, as you may read; And ye holy i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart rejoyce, and lift up your heads towards the day of Redemption, and own your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration here on earth that you may be gat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered to the Fathers with that which comes from above, and that ſpirit which perfects the juſt, and caſts out the unjuſt, where are the dogs and Adulterers, and ſuch as know not God, and where the hearts are gathered to the Fathers in God there the earth is bleſſed, whoſe God is the Lord, who have received the ſpirit from on high, and are filled with the Holy Ghoſt, as <hi>Stephen</hi> was who ſaw heaven open, who was full of God, whom the great Profeſſors ſtoned, who was full of wrath, and yet ſaid they looked for his coming from Scriptures, yet like mad men run upon him &amp; deſtroyed his Temple, ſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed their temple w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they thought to uphold, who reſiſted God the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe he had no place in them, who could not receive the light of the world, nor his word could find place in them, but in ſuch as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt out it found place, whoſe bodies were the Temple of the liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g God, as he hath ſaid, <hi>I will dwell in them and walk in them,</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>och</hi> walked within, with God in ſpirit, and was not, &amp; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad wrought all his works in him; &amp; <hi>Jeremy</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> full of the fury of the Lord; &amp; <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was the ſon of man; And <hi>Daniel</hi> had the ſpirit of them m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt High God the ſpirit of light &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Paul</hi> had the Son of God revealed in him, the ſame that he Preached, and ſaid they that knew not Chriſt in them were reprobates, and he that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit; And to <hi>David</hi> the Lord ſaid, <hi>Thou art my Son this day have I begotten thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>David</hi> declared it, and the Saints were begotten of God, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62425:31"/>
partakers of the Divine nature, and confeſſed the Father and the Son in them, and that the Son of God was come and had given them an underſtanding, which they that looked for him to come without, underſtood not, who beat him in their Synagogues and ſhamefully intreated him, becauſe they knew not the Father nor the Son, but ſaid he was to come; And they that had the Son had Life, and the reſt was children of wrath, filled with wrath, and ſo the Father and the Son ſupt with ſuch as had them, and the Lord was at their Table, and they fed with him in his ſufferings and blood, and the reſt made a large Profeſſion of him, but fed at the table of Devils, and theſe grew great in violence and ſtrong to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and ſhed blood, and the other excelled in meekneſs and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in ſuffering, and here were they ſeparated into life and death never like to meet more.</p>
               <p>And here now may all read the worſhip in ſpirit in ſuch as know God in ſpirit, and the worſhip in Letter in them that have not God, and know not what they worſhip, and theſe know not what they do who know not what they worſhip, and the Son of God ſaith, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do,</hi> who ſaith they worſhip they know not what, who worſhip not in ſpirit, who worſhip in their thoughts of God, but not the Spirit of God in poſſeſſion and knowledge, who think they do God ſervice to kill and deſtroy the Temple of God, becauſe they know not him in themſelves that is worſhipped therein, as Chriſt hath foretold, and muſt be fulfilled at the coming of the Holy Ghoſt; And when God deſcends from heaven to walk on Earth in his Temples, and to require his worſhip to himſelf out of all Sects and traditions, this is his entertainment from all that look for him in obſervations, whoſe coming is within, and his Kingdom is within you.</p>
               <p>And now to you he is come of whom you have been long talking, and in that way he appears among you of which you are Preaching; The <hi>Jews</hi> had but the propheſies and ſhadows to know him by reading without them, but you read and Preach in words of the lively pattern in ſpirit, and have heard of the ſame Life and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which now he bears againſt you in his Temples, and when he comes you cannot receive him who ſuffers the ſame things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. Oh <hi>England</hi> how wilt thou ſtand in judgement, what wilt thou plead for thy ſelf, when he ariſes to judgement, whoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62425:31"/>
Teſtimony againſt thee is drawing to an end? what will be thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and who wilt thou ſay thou took him to be, who now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures ſuch contradiction againſt himſelf, ſuch haling, beatings, ſcourgings, and mockings, and baniſhings, impriſonings and death, without reſiſtings? haſt not thou heard of him before he came, that thou might have known in this thy day the things of thy peace? haſt thou not read of him that is ſent to ſeek his loſt, in Temples and Synagogues, in Markets, and where the greateſt of the people be, in which manner he now appears, and being refuſed of the rich, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the poor in the high wayes and hedges, and yet hath no where to lay his own head, haſt thou not heard of the everlaſting way of his walkings in Prophets and Apoſtles, and his pilgrimage in their bodies upon ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, who was ever a ſtranger in the world at his coming from Heaven? what ſpirit wilt thou ſay this is which hath conformed ſo many at this day, who was amongſt you like wolves to devour others, now to ſuffer the ſpoiling of their goods, and torturings of their bodies, and taking away their lives without ſeeking the leaſt revenge, wilt thou at that day ſay thou had thought it had been the ſpirit of the Devil, as many of you now doth, though in your conſciences otherwiſe convinced?</p>
               <p>Alas for thee, how art thou wept over at this day? And what a lamentable ſorrow hath many of the Lords ſervants for thee, whom thou haſt caſt in holes and priſons for their obedience to God and teſtimony of their conſcience towards God in them, whoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſufferings, and unparaleld cruelties are no more valued with thee then if they were dogs? and this hath gone throughout thee from the leaſt to the greateſt till there be very few left which are not wholly hardned, ſo that to hear of theſe evil dealings exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the innocent doth no more enter your hearts, then the rain enters a rock; wherefore our ſouls are troubled for you, and our hopes concerning your healing grows daily leſs, and our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in the Lord Jeſus daily greater, haſting to the full, and what will you do in the end thereof? Or whom ſhall we take to witneſs for you? or may you be compared with any that ever hardned themſelves in theſe wayes and eſcaped deſtruction, that our hopes might revive and our prayers not ceaſe, did ever any thus deny the life of what you Preach in words your ſelves, and which ſome of you have meaſure felt and ſuffered for, and have
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62425:32"/>
been anſwered in by the Lord, and your eyes have ſeen the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Almighty, and how dreadful it hath been both upon Kings, Prieſts and Rulers for reſiſting? Ah how much better had it been for you never to have known theſe things, which you have ſeen, read and Preached, then now that they ſhould be fulfilled upon you to the uttermoſt? how well had it been for you had you been as thoſe you call heathen, rather then to Profeſs Chriſt and thus act againſt him at his coming, even in the ſame way your ſelves Preach him?</p>
               <p>Alas, alas, what hath the innocent done, why he thus is uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you? doth he cry againſt ſin, againſt pride, againſt falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, againſt corrupt Rulers, corrupt Teachers, corrupt Lawyers, &amp;c. And with much meekneſs bears his witneſs againſt theſe evils in you for a teſtimony of light to your words, whom he hath lifted up in wrath and zeal and judgement againſt the ſame things in the perſons of others? and will not this ariſe againſt you of which you are witneſſes all in one generation? But ſayſt thou, he breaks the peace, and breaks our Law, and is unmannerly, &amp;c. But was he not ever ſo accounted, and is he not now in the ſame way he ever walked? what could that peace do for you (could you keep it whole) which is broken by reproving ſin and deceit? Is there any peace to the wicked from God? and will he keep that Law which will not give him liberty to Reign in his Temples, and to lead his people by his Spirit? or will you plead that Law againſt him in judgement when he comes to deal with you, who ſhould know his Law written in your hearts to limit you, and not your Laws to limit him, not your manners muſt not bind the conſcience where he is known to be King? and this you know is truth and have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it againſt others, and now cannot own it, will not the Laws of Chriſt and the manners of Chriſt of which you read in Scripture agree with your Government and peace, who calls for his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to come amongſt you, and profeſs to rule according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? how will this ſtand at that day when you muſt not be your own Judges, nor by your own Laws? And why is he counted your enemy ſeeing his appearance now is in love to give you light out of this (for your Eternal ſalvation) againſt which he will certainly come in Judgement to condemnation? Have you not heard of the love of the Father to the world, who ſends his Son to lay down his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62425:32"/>
Life therein for a light to the world, that whoſoever believeth therein might not be condemned? can you read and confeſs this life laid down in the Prophets, in C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, in the Apoſtles, in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and in all in whom this righte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blood hath been ſhed from <hi>Abel</hi> to your time, and can you not ſay they were blind Prieſt and People who could not ſee this innocent ſuffer in his ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances? And what will you ſay of your ſelves, ſeeing the ſame teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is before your eyes, but not received? was ever his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſo increaſed in ſo little a time, and for ſuch little fooliſh things (as your ſelves calls them) which though they ſeem little yet much innocent blood hath been ſhed, and this life is laid down daily in many? And why ſhould you count that ſo little, which your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren count dearer then their precious life? Is there any thing makes it ſo but the tenderneſs of the one, and hardneſs of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? But ſay you, they are guilty of their own blood to ſuffer for ſuch fooliſh things, but who is their executioners? do not you ſuffer fools daily, they ſhall witneſs againſt you, that there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it more then folly? have you not read that God chuſeth the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and baſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed things to bring to nought things that are, and weak things to confound the mighty? and can you read and Preach this and not ſee it fulfilled nor underſtand without a meaning? then take heed how you call that fooliſh which God hath choſen to lay down his life in for a witneſs againſt the murtherer in the wiſe men of the world, will you call that fooliſhneſs whereby the myſteries of God comes to be manifeſt, &amp; that which he hath choſen to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in openly in his Temples and his worſhip, his ſervice, and his ſuffering long in meekneſs, and the Devil in his Temples, with his ſervants, his pride, his raſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs and cruelty, and to lay each open to the ſimpleſt heart by their fruits, which have been long covered withwords, but now every one that knows a Wolfe from a Lamb may ſee and cannot be deceived? will you call this little which diſcovers ſo great a depth of deceit ſo cloſely hid, and opens the painted Sepulchres, and ſearches the heart of the deceitful, laying it open to your ſelves and others, which elſe you could not have known nor believed if you were told it? could many of you have believed the Prince of pride had ruled in you, till you ſee him act you in cruelty on your Brethren becauſe they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62425:33"/>
cannot worſhip you? or could you have believed that the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer had been there till you proceed to caſt into priſons your brethren and keep them there till death for theſe little things? And theſe things ſome ſuffer under you for a witneſs, and the reſt are ſpared (though that ſpirit would have none to live) that the Scriptures may be fulfilled, Satan ſhall caſt ſome of you into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp;c. And are not theſe things manifeſtly laid open to your ſelves and all that are not willingly blind, and alſo the contrary Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus where theſe things are patiently endured? And will you call this fooliſhneſs, which thus leaves all the world without excuſe, and prepares all for righteous Judgement? many had little thought theſe little things ſhould have opened ſuch great ſecrets, or this folly have confounded ſuch wiſdom, when a ſubtle ſpirit hath been ſome years getting knowledge, and words and Religion to make himſelf fair without, that others may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be a ſuffering Saint, and one of theſe little things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes in his way, which diſcover him to be a devouring Wolfe in a moment; may not the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e then truely ſay the weakneſs of God is greater then the wiſdom of men, and God hath choſen fooliſh things to confound the wiſe? And now the Scripture is fulfilled to your face whether you (ſeeing) can perceive or no, and the rock of offence is laid and the ſtone of ſtumbling though he be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; and he is come whom we have looked for, in the thouſands of his Saints, and the head over his Church, and his body he is preparing daily that the Fathers will may be done in Earth, and that he may take vengeance of them that know him not, nor will receive his teſtimony, who will not believe his light that now ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, though he be come after their own Preaching, and many are his witneſſes at this day; glory to his brightneſs, and let the Son ariſe and Reign for ever in whom alone the Scriptures are now fulfilling, and the builders re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject him, and the wicked make prey upon him where he turns from iniquity, and the ſpoiling of goods is ſuffered joyfully, and the havock is made of the Church, and he is taken from priſon and from Judgement, and the reproach of many he bears, and the back is given to the ſmiter, and he that ſues at the Law for the coat may take the Cloak alſo, and he that would have the Hat take the head and body alſo without reſiſting, and prayers and tears is ſhed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62425:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for them that hate and deſpitefully uſe him, and goods are taken away and not asked again, and this is our beloved, and this is his voice, and his ſheep knows it, and follows him, and thus it is w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten of him, and thus it is now read, and glory to him that liveth and reigneth for ever, who was, and is, and is come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>TO THE RANTERS.</head>
               <p>VVO unto you Ranters of all ſorts, the day of your tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment approacheth, your cup is almoſt full, your time draws near an end, you are ſed, you are grown full for the ſlaughter, your ſwelling is reached up to heaven, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Innocent and Juſt one in you cries on high; above all people you have dealt evil with the Lord, and treachcrouſly betrayed the tender proffer of his Spirit, you have murthered the babe in the womb, and he hath not reſiſted but intreated. How many gentle reproofs hath he viſited you with? And with what Love and Faithfulneſſe hath he followed you from one of your evils to another, calling to you in ſecret, in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and out of ſeaſon, before the act of your wickedneſſe, in the act of it, and after you have done it? If by any means he might have overtaken you, and prevented your ruine, and won you again, that he might have done you good and ſaved you from the paths of the Deſtroyer, all which is written where it cannot be rooted out againſt the day of vengeance, although you have done what you can to ſtop the mouth of Gods wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in you, and to ſtifle the Juſt leaſt he ſhould reprove you, or give you light in your dark by paths, wherein you have walked towards the Lord as wild Colts and fed Horſes, refuſing his teachings or corrections, ſtrengthening one another againſt the faithful witneſſe of Truth when you have b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n wounded
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62425:34"/>
therewith, and have belied the Lord, and ſaid it is not he, and if it be he, let him make me better; and I cannot make my ſelf; and if the Devil be in me let him caſt him out; and that ſin and Righteouſneſſe is all one to God; and many of you openly denying God; and much more ſuch blaſphemies out of you hath proceeded, all which the Innocent Lamb hath born ſince the day he firſt invited you, and the Juſt Lord who is in the midſt of you hath ſeen it, and of you he will take revenge for the Innocent ones ſake, whom he will eaſe of his enemy.</p>
               <p>Oh the terrible day that I have ſeen approaching towards you, and the miſery that is coming nigh when you ſhall be dealt withal, as you have done againſt the Meek and the Holy Seed, which hath ſtirred in you unto life, which you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed and murthered for your luſts, treacherouſly have dealt and treacherouſly will you be dealt withal; then ſhal you know that there is a God of Power and Judgement when you ſhall be as a mad Bull in a Net, and the Fire of God underneath you, then ſhall you chuſe death and it ſhall flie from you, who have refuſed the way of Life and puft at it, and you who have ſcorned the Light ſhall know Chains of Darkneſſe. Ah how have you mocked at reproof, the Lord hath heard your light anſwers, and hath born your mocking, and you have made him to ſerve under your luſte, he is oppreſſed, and grieved, and broken with your whoriſh hearts, and you have made heavy the burthen of the meek and lowly, againſt whom you have ſported, and have not conſidered that all this is againſt your own Souls, and to make ſtrong bonds for your own Necks, which you muſt know and feel when the juſt ariſes to plead againſt you for all that is written againſt you: Verily dread is upon me when I behold your end, and the way you have to go, and how few there are to be ſaved. Alas for you, how have you heaped deceit, and filled your Veſſels with that which the pure God abhors? You have eaten and drunken your own damnation while you have ſerved your luſts, you have choſen deceit rather then truth, and therewith ſhall you be deceived when you look for reſt; you have got words and ſought out cunning wayes to ſtop the way of judgment in you, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62425:34"/>
is your cup become full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or condemnation from the Lord God of power, you are filled with the names of blaſphemy againſt the moſt high, yea, it is written, <hi>He hath marked you out, he hath ſet himſelf againſt you, and while you are building a wall of falſehood, is he preparing deſtruction, and is watching over you for evil and not for good, and your wall you have made of cunning deceits will ſtand betwixt you and Salvation, and keep you from find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place of Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And you high minded Profeſſors alſo who have gotten the wiſdom of words, and have preached high things of God and Chriſt, which in you is not wrought nor fulfilled but in a lie: this will be required at your hands with truth, and your own words ſhall ariſe againſt you in judgment, and when you ſhould come to him that ſhould anſwer in your behalf, your Wiſdom and Knowledg which you have got in that Nature which hath oppreſſed him, will ſtand in your way as thick Darkneſſe which you cannot remove nor paſſe; then ſhall you curſe your God who hath ſet you on Preaching Words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Life, and lies by which the Spirit of truth in you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſuffered and been denied, and Gods Witneſſe lie waſte, and been reſiſted in its gentle Calls, Motions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs: All which a juſt hand and unreſiſtable will bring upon you, in that day when Chains of Darkneſſe hath compaſſed you in the Horrible Pit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Deceipt Diſcovered by its Fruits.</head>
               <p>YOu that call the Children of the Light blaſphemers and Seducers, and many evil Names you give out to People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, becauſe they Preach Chriſt the light of the world, and Chriſt for Righteouſneſſe and Perfection, &amp;c. Hear what Blaſphemy, and Seducing, and Deceiving is, and who are the Deceivers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:62425:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
They were blaſpemers who ſaid they were <hi>Jews</hi> and were not, and this was <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> in Gods account, <hi>To profeſſe in words what they were not in works,</hi> Rev. 2. 9. And they were blaſphemers who ſaid, <hi>He that wrought the works of righteouſneſſe was of the Devil,</hi> Mark 3. 22, 28, 29, 30. And <hi>James</hi> ſaid, <hi>They Blaſphemed that Holy Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e by which the Saints were called, who drew them before Judgment S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ats, and Oppreſſed them.</hi> Jam. 2, 6, 7. And <hi>Saul</hi> blaſphemed in perſecuting for Conſcience towards Chriſt. Now this God call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>blaſphemy, Falſly to take upon them the Name of a</hi> Jew, <hi>ſeeing the</hi> Jewes <hi>were to be a Holy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Lord, and to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r his Holy Name before all the world in Righteouſneſſe and Truth, and the fruits of his Spirit; which Name they who had not the Life did blaſpheme, by taking the Name of a</hi> Jew. And Chriſt call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it <hi>blaſphemy, to condemn the fruits of that Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be of the Devil.</hi> And the Apoſtle calls it <hi>blaſphemy, To hale before the Judgment Seats<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and perſecute the poor that God had choſen out of the world.</hi> Theſe were the old blaſphemers in Gods account, and their children be in the ſame ſteps till this day, and therein the truth finds them, and uncovers them.</p>
               <p>So come to your Rule, and be tryed as you are in <hi>Deed,</hi> and not in <hi>Words,</hi> in Gods account and not in your Own: This is the blaſphemy, to ſay, <hi>You are Chriſtians, and are not:</hi> To ſay, <hi>You are in Chriſt, and are not:</hi> To ſay, <hi>You are of God, and do the Works of the Devil that old Murtherer and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter:</hi> To ſay, <hi>Such as do the works of God are blaſphemers, and to Oppreſſe your brethren for conſcience ſake.</hi> And this <hi>blaſphemy</hi> exceeds your Fathers, by how much the Name of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels the Name of a <hi>Jew.</hi> Will you bring forth the abominable fruits that God hates, and cover them with the Name of Chriſt, and father them upon the Spirit of Chriſt, and ſay you are in Chriſt, and Redeemed, and Baptized into him, and have Communion in him, and get up Likeneſſes, and Imitations from the Letter to cover you with in a nature contrary to Chriſt? And is not this the Height of Deceit and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy?</p>
               <p>What, is the Name of Chriſt, and the Redemption of Chriſt, the Death of Chriſt, the Baptiſm of Chriſt, the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62425:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of Chriſt, the Communion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, and the Words of Chriſt become a Cloak for the Works of Wickedneſſe? And doth not this blaſpheme his Name, his Words, his Spirit, his Ordinances, and his People, and all his Holy things, and cauſe them to be <hi>blaſphemed</hi> amongſt the Heathen, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World? But to preach Chriſt the Light of the world, and to confeſſe him in us, ſo far as we feel the power of his Spirit taking us out of the power of Sin, and Conforming us to himſelf, and to bring forth the fruits of his Spirit in Truth and Righteouſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe; this doth not blaſphem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but in ſuch he is Honoured, who ſhew forth his vertues and walk in his Spirit, ſuch exalt his Name. This was <hi>Pauls</hi> work when he had left off to blaſpheme.</p>
               <p>Now come to your Rule and be tryed, it tells you who are Chriſts, and who are Antichriſts, Deceivers, and Blaſphemers, and they are known by their Works, and not by their Words. It ſaith, <hi>They that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh with the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and luſts. And if Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin: And as many as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Christ: And as you have received Chriſt Jeſus, ſo walk in him: And he that ſaith he abideth in him ought himſelf ſo to walk, even as he walked: and ye are all one in Chriſt Jeſus: And if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature, and all things are of God: And he that ſaith he know: Chriſt, and keeps not his Commandements, is a Liar.</hi> And this is the blaſphemer, who covers himſelf with the words of truth, but is an enemy to the life.</p>
               <p>Now here is the teſtimony of Truth, lay it to the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your lives, and meaſure your ſelves therewith, and we will meaſure our ſelves therewith alſo; and let Truth judge the Deceiver and Liar, and Blaſphemer by his Fruits, and where he hath his Seat. What will Truth ſay where Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe is found? Have ſuch Crucified the Affections? Have Proud men Crucified their Luſts? Have Wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons Crucified the Fleſh? Have Swearers, Lyars, and curſed Speakers put off the body of Sin? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d where theſe work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, where there is Envie, Strife, Suits, and Contentions? Is this to put on Chriſt, or to be all one in him? Where Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Scorning, Back-biting, and Slandering is, and the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62425:36"/>
Veſſels filled with ſuch Wickedneſſe, are all things of God? And are ſuch baptized into his death, or planted into his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection? And are not they blaſphemers who perſecute others for Conſcience towards God? But to preach Chriſt to be the Light of the World, and the Hope of Glory in the Saints our Life, our Righteouſneſſe and Perfection, and to ſuffer for it is no blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>Now here is your Meaſure, and with Truth are you mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, weighed, and tryed: Your Baptiſmes, your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, your Redemption, your Death and Reſurrection, and your life Eternal: And in the light you and we are ſeen, and with the life thereof you are found (who bring forth theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fruits) to be under the power of ſin, unredeemed, and out of Chriſt the life, deceiving your own ſouls and others of the righteous Inheritance amongſt them that are Sanctified, and blaſpheming the holy Name of Chriſt, and grieving his holy Spirit, by profeſſing that in his Name which you have not, and by your evil deeds acted under his Name whereby it is polluted, which was not given for a cover to ſuch Works.</p>
               <p>In this holy Name of Chriſt hath God placed his Covenant and Life, and in theſe Holy things did Holy men and women meet with God, worſhip him, and dwell with him in Spirit, as his houſe in which he was ſeen and walked: And are theſe now become a cover for a Den of thieves, a habitation and hiding for all the abominations now acted in the world? Is not this the height of Blaſphemy and Deceit, thus to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane his holy Name, and turn it into a lie, as though all theſe abominable things were therein, or that he owned ſuch as live in them?</p>
               <p>Now lay your words and your works in the true Ballance, and weigh them with the Words of Life and Power of his Name, and meaſure of Truth and Honeſty, and lye not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth: But you that are under the power of theſe wickedneſſes, and in bondage thereto, who ſee (and are not aſhamed to ſay) you cannot but commit theſe abominations while you live, do not lie againſt the work of Chriſt, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath Redeemed you, when you are yet in this bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62425:36"/>
neither count his blood an unholy thing, in ſaying you are waſhed, nor his Work imperfect, nor mix it with the work of the Devil; but give to each his own, that thereby they may be known, and in what Name every thing is wrought; for now is Truth come to try you, and he is appearing who will have his own, and nothing but his own, under what pretence ſoever. Now is the Heir of Righteouſneſſe come to ſeek the fruit of his own; ſtand ſtill you that uſe thoſe high words againſt o hers, and ſee how the Lord is dealt with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you at this day: Did not he plant a Holy Vine to bring forth to himſelf of his own Nature and Image? and have you let this be over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>run with weeds, while you have been aſleep in your ſloth and idleneſſe, cares and pleaſures of the world, till all be filled with bryars and thorns, and corrupt plants that now are ſpread and bring forth? And now the Lord is come who is the light of the world, to ſeek fruits of his own, and will you hold him forth theſe curſed fruits, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them with his Name, as though they were his, and ſeek to force them upon him whether he will or no, and fall violently upon him if he deny them?</p>
               <p>Now if this be not ſo, what means this? That when any one in his Name is ſent to reprove ſin in the Streets or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets where it abounds, and in the Name of Chriſt to declare againſt falſe worſhips, never ſet up by him (which hath been his manner in all his appearances) and to call for what is his own, and to deny the works of the Devil, that preſently all is in an uproar, and a tumult raiſed, pulling and beating, and haling to Priſon, beaten in Markets, beaten in your Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, ſhamefully intreated in your Streets, and all for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offence, but becauſe he calls for his own, and denies what is not of him? Doth not this Blaſpheme that Holy Name by which they are called, and which your ſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe? Teacher cryes away with him, and tumult cryes away with him, its not fit he ſhould live. And what uſage he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives from you in his members is openly ſeen, and God is daily bringing your works to light. Now let the wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n heart, who can diſcern the ſigns of the times, read, if the Parable be not fulfilled upon you Husbandmen: And will
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62425:37"/>
you guild this Cup over with fine words, forms and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and call them Deceivers and Blaſphemers, who in love to your souls and obedience to Chriſt tells you of it, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies againſt it, in all long ſuffering and patience? Who will be found the deceivers and the deceived, when your guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d covers comes to be pulled off, and you muſt drink of the Cup your ſelves as you have filled: and this is certainly near at hand to come upon you, and you are haſting towards it a pace, your Cup is almoſt full, and with the light are you ſeen; Hath not the Lamb ſet up his Teſtimony againſt you almoſt in every place of the Nation? How many Towns have you in which the Innocent have not ſuffered violence for crying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inſt ſin, in the Name of Chriſt, calling for the fruits of Righteouſneſs? How many Priſons have you that do not ſpeak your cruelty? How many Counties have you in which Innocent blood hath not been ſhed which daily ſpeaks? How many of your Synagogues have the Children of light born witneſs in againſt your evil wayes, wherein they have been beaten, haled, pulled and puniſhed? And all this you drink up as a thing of nought, and are yet thirſtier then at firſt? Are theſe the works of Chriſt, or of the old Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer?</p>
               <p>Wherefore ceaſe to Blaſpheme, for you are meaſured by that which will not lie, and with your own Rule are you found in the works of the old deceiver, and the old perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors; and in their Oppoſition and Blaſphemy againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, where it teſtifies againſt your evil deeds. So ſeeing you are found in the works of the old Perſecutors, and in their nature, take to you their name, for that is truth, and will be your Inheritance amongſt them; and ceaſe to Blaſpheme the Name of Chriſt by taking it upon you to cover theſe abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and hide your ſin from your own eyes, and ſo deceive your own Souls, and others that are blind; but who comes in the Name of Chriſt, comes in the light to prove you openly, and ſees you, and gives light in the life of Chriſt for all to diſcern betwixt the Lamb and the Wolſ, by their nature and not by their cloathing.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is the Holy annointing wherewith all that are in him
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62425:37"/>
ſees out of theſe things to be led, and every appearance of his from <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt murtherer till this day, declares theſe to be the works of the Devil and by works of a contrary nature doth witneſs againſt them; In which life he is the light of the world, who though he be in the midſt of Gods Throne (ſeen ſo to his own) yet as a Lamb ſlain among theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean beaſts, ſhining forth in the life of Meekneſſe, Holineſſe, Patience and Long-ſuffering, enduring all things from his enemies: which Light and Life, though to she wiſdom of the wiſe world it appears poor, baſe and contemptible, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the builders rejected; yet it is full of Grace and Truth, and hath power with God over the Devil, and all theſe his works, and by Faith in his Name, and by the vertue of his Nature, all that are in him bear his Teſtimony againſt the worlds works and nature: for in that Name is Gods Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Life and Peace, and the Ark of his ſtrength and ſafety in the great deſtruction that is to come upon the world for theſe things: and he is ever at the Arm of Gods ſtrength, and ſits at his right hand in heavenly places, and with him to gather and ſave his Elect from the ends of the earth; and by his ſufferings to redeem them from under thoſe ungodly powers, and to break the bonds of iniquity; and therefore they who are gathered into this Name, holds it as a Holy Power, and dare not blaſpheme it, but ſay, Let every one that nameth the Name of Chriſt depart from iniquity. Which Name to ſuch is ſalvation, and ſtrength, and righteouſneſſe, meekneſs and peace.</p>
               <p>Ah blind people, that have eyes and ſee not! What is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of your profeſſion of Names, your Forms and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and how is God departed out of all (as to you) and your houſe is become deſolate, and where light, truth and peace ſhould dwell, its become a habitation of devourers, a place of Owls, and Dragons, and Night-birds, and beaſts of prey? ſuch ſpirits rule in all your holy things in which you truſt. You cry the name of Chriſt, but ſee not, nor is your eye anointed: You cry the name of Jeſus, but are not ſaved from your ſins: You cry Chriſt is your King, but have not peace: You cry great is the Lord with your lips,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62425:38"/>
but the Devil prevails in your hearts, and carries you captive at his will, contrary to the will of the Lord. So you have got the words of Saints, but the life you have loſt; Sheep in words, but Wolves in nature, and ſo are in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs againſt ſuch as retain the power of what you profeſs. Now are not theſe vain words you truſt in, which doth not ſave? This is the deceiver you tell on, who makes people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in a lie, and now he is found in your own boſom; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the day which hath brought his works to light, glory to God for evermore. Wherefore let not your own thoughts deceive you, and lead you to caſt upon others that which in your ſelves ſound, but leave your vain and evil thoughts of others, and judge your own ſelves with the light of life, and meaſure your works with truth, and not with thoughts. Did not they that perſecuted the Prophets think they did God ſervice? And they that perſecuted Chriſt thought the ſame; and they that perſecuted the Apoſtles and Saints of old knew not that they perſecuted Chriſt Jeſus, but thought they did well to puniſh Hereticks and Blaſphemers; and they that flew the Martyrs were of the ſame ſpirit, and ſo of the ſame mind. And now come to your ſelves and your thoughts in this your work, which is the ſame at this day, and many of you have the ſame thoughts, though ſome of you act clearly againſt what you ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and ſo exceed all your fore-fathers: and now ſee who are Deceivers and Blaſphemers, and where the Lamb is led to the ſlaughter.</p>
               <p>Ah, you teachers of theſe Nations, ſhould you thus have uſed your liberty you had given of God from under the dark power that ruled (in part) in the Biſhops, under which ſome of you ſuffered? Was it not then in your hearts, that if you had but liberty, you would go on to the rooting our of the reliques of Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and Idol-worſhips, and Perfecution? Should you not have gon on with ſingleneſs of heart, as you had liberty, to the end? Then had you been faithful to God and the Nations, then had you been as openers of the holy paths for men to walk in, and breakers of oppreſſion, and men ſhould have called you the bleſſed of God, then had you not inherited this curſed thing ſet up by your fathers
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62425:38"/>
the old perſecusors and oppreſſors, (whoſe children you are now found to appear) then had you uot been at this day found fighting for their fat Benefits which ſpued them out, ſuing your people for Tithes, <hi>Pigs, Geeſe, Smoke,</hi> and ſuch like traſh, haling poor people to priſon, and ſpoiling their Houſes and lands for your bellies: you had been at this day in a more honourable work than raking in theſe Dung-hils. The Lord ſhould not have needed to have called your own hearers from under your elbows, and ſent them againſt you into your Meetings to declare your ſhame openly, and to caſt this dung in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aces, laying open your deceitful works and worſhips, which falls ſo heavie upon you, that you have not ſtrength left to ſtand before the guilt thereof, nor have any defence, but either to flie, or cry out to the earthly Powers to help you againſt him who is now become your Adverſary. It was not thus with you while you were ſufferers for ſtanding faithful to what you then knew of Gods new work. I appeal to that of God in your own Conſciences, if then a ſilly boy or girl, or man or woman, had asked you a queſtion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Doctrine or Manners, if you would have uſed either your feet to flie, or your hand to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mite, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cried, Away with him, Officer take him to priſon, Magiſtrate make a Law againſt him. Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Acts were then abomination to you, you had then another weapon, even a meaſure of the Spirit to inform the weak with meekneſſe, and to convince gain-ſayers: But then you were ſufferers your ſelves for your Conſcience, and ſo the caſe is changed with you, and the Spirit alſo, as far as the ſufferer is from the perſecuter: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here the Deceiver keeps you blind, in that you keep the old form you then had, but proſſeſſed with another ſpirit: So your ſticking in the form hath deceived you of the ſuffering Spirit, and the power of meekneſſe, which had you been led by the Spirit of the Lamb, you had been at this day in the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, not tormentors of thoſe that are. Have not I heard ſome of you in publick declare, That if a Church had perſecution in it for Conſcience ſake upon any account whatſoever, it needed no further Trial to prove it to be of the Devil, and not of the Church of Chriſt. But ſince
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62425:39"/>
the ſame perſon (though no mean one of account amongſt the fineſt ſort of Teachers) have commanded them to priſon who came but into the Synagogue, and ſpoke not one word. Alas for your Souls! how are you fallen under the curſed thing, that you ſhould be they who are left to fill up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of what the Biſhops came ſhort of. Ah! how are you to be pitied? Will not your cutting them off riſe againſt you, And will not God avenge their bloud upon you who have condemned their perſons, but juſtifie the things for which they were cut off, by adding manifold thereto in the ſame nature. God is Judge this day, and his light in your hearts, how you have dealt with him and his inheritance, by which you ſhould have been led out of theſe things, going before you into the Kingdom of God, but are now found in the work of gain-ſaying ſuch as are coming out of darkneſſe into light, neither entring your ſelves, nor ſuffering them that would. So let truth for ever ſtand upon the head of the deceiver and blaſphemer, and let ſuch as are ſeduced by them be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall delivered. And bleſſed be the Lamb for ever, whoſe Life is this day become a light to divide the Sheep from the Wolves, that he may come to Judgment.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="message">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:62425:39"/>
            <head>A MESSAGE FROM THE SPIRIT of TRUTH, Unto the Holy Seed.</head>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>
                  <hi>To the</hi> Reader.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>YOu lovers and followers of the Light, to you is this meſsage ſent, in it abide, that the glory of the only begotten of the Father, you may behold, and be changed from glory to glory: fill not your heads, but feel the life of what in this followings paper is declared. For though the Thief, the Boaster, the proud and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted ones have, or may cover themſelves with like words; yet this birth never was, is, or ſhall be brought forth, but by the eſpouſed Virgin; pure, chaſte, and ſpotleſse, true and abiding innocency; far diſtant from all feigned purity, which many being puffed up in their vain minds, have or may intrude into things they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62425:40"/>
know not, and ſo deceive the ſimple by a voluntary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and worſhipping of Angels: theſe hold not fast the head which gives the life to every member; he that is without beginning of days, or end of life; by whom, and for whom all things were made: to him ſhall every knee bow, who filleth all in all, of whoſe fulneſs he hath received, grace for grace, who in theſe following lines ſalutes the whole elect of God every where, plentifully giving forth of the great Myſtery of godlineſs, hidden from ages and generations, now made manifeſt to the meek and upright in heart, who in the unfeigned love abide, which endures for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. T.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>DEar friends, Brethren, and Siſters, of the Seed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> partakers with him in the holy call, and who in his faith wait for that glory, and inheritance immortal, which every one of you ſhall receive at the appearance of the great God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, to you all be peace, truth and love increaſed, wherein you may be eſtabliſhed to the end of your calling.</p>
               <p>That which is ſet before me in the Spirit of truth, and for which my ſoul travels, and breaths after in the whole Creation (but eſpecially in you who are already called thereunto) I am moved to impart unto you, thereby to ſtir you up earneſtly, to preſs on towards the appearance of that to which you are called in one, which is no other then what hath been holden forth from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, even the only begotten of the Father, filled with grace and truth, for the obtaining whereof, you that are faithful have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the delights of this preſent world, and do daily undergo the enmity thereof. Of whoſe appearance many of you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62425:40"/>
a certain hope which cannot be ſhaken, and a meaſure of him, ſome are come to in the ſame Spirit, who have ſeen, felt, and handled of his appearance, and have received of his fulneſs, wherein alone you excell, and are able to hold forth that life i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the power of obedience, meekneſſe, and fear which no form nor knowledge without is able to bear or bring forth, which is that alone wherein I rejoyce in you, and not onely ſo, but find cauſe in heart to magnifie that goodneſſe, and glorious power of God, already manifeſted in you, and through you to the world, whoſe praiſes will daily increaſe, as his vertues appear in you; which that you, and all the number of called ones may increaſe, and grow to the age, ſtature, and full appearance of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt, is the full deſire of my ſoul, and that which will give us an aſſured joy and perfect peace in one, when knowledg will vaniſh, and that which is in part ſhall be done away.</p>
               <p>Wherefore you that have received the Spirit of Prophecy, and that light out of darkneſſe, which lets you ſee what manner of one the Son of God muſt be at his appearing in Spirit and power, holineſs, and great glory, I beſeech you that none of you ſit down at reſt in this ſight, nor be you puffed up therewith, as though you had already attained, leſt thereby the Enemy prevail to aſſault you above what is meet, and ſo others leſſe in wiſdome, who are more lowly in ſpirit ſtep in before you, and obtain that Crown and glory to which you were called, and ſo while you feed on the knowledge you looſe, the life, but that every one waite in the light to feel the power and life, of the Son of God manifeſt in your bodies giving you victory over your own ſpirits, and raiſing you up out of death into the life of the Prophecies, that you may all know the true worſhip in Spirit, and what you bow unto, that henceforth you may be ſervants of righteouſneſſe, begotten and not made, which only hath food able to ſatisfie your thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſting ſouls, that you may all feel the onely begotten of God in vertue, and power, working mightily the work of the Father, and deſtroying the work of the devil in every particular, for hereunto were you firſt called, that you ſhould inherit eternal life and power. the true riches of grace in righteouſneſs, and to receive a Kingdome that cannot be moved, but that is able to keep you againſt all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the enemy, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iches is Gods onely begotten, in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62425:41"/>
whom is received of the perfect fulneſſe of God, which is only able to ſatisfie all fears, and ſupply all wants, in all who attain to his appearance.</p>
               <p>And further I beſeech you, that you ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie not your ſelves one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a feeling of this working in you, but that you diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend an entrance thereinto, that you may put him on whom the Father begetteth and formeth in you, that you ſouls may be bathed and anointed therein. And not only ſo, but that you bring him forth before all men, even him the only begotten Son of God in meekneſs, long-ſuffering, in patience, in righteouſneſs, in godly holineſſe, and all his vertues; the living image of him, by whom he is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: that it may appear to all men whoſe you are, and who poſſeſſeth the veſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, and what he is that appears therein; that it may be ſeen and confeſſed that God is in you of a truth revealed in his only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, For this is he, to whom at his appearance every tongue ſhall confeſſe, and every heart be ſtruck with fear; though the form of his beauty, and viſage of his glory hath amongſt falſe Births, and fained profeſſions) been more marred then any mans, who inſtead of bringing forth into the world the only begotten of God, to convince and condemn the world of all ungodlineſs, and ſave them from it, have brought forth the conceivings of their own brains, and the child born to them is no Saviour, but their birth hath left them in the world, and one with it, who are now turning the words of Chriſt againſt his works, and their power to withſtand his appearance in others, who is the ſame which was, and is, and is to come to all generations.</p>
               <p>So that inſtead of holding forth that ſpiritual power of perfect Redemption from above, to ſave his people from their ſins, and ſet them at liberty from the bondage of corruption to ſerve God in the new man, the Son of Righteouſneſſe, of peace, and holineſſe, Gods image, there appears the Son of wickedneſſe in every form, at liberty, and pleaded for, the Image and power of all unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ungodlineſſe, preached and ſet up: ſo that the very faith and hope of Gods appearance in this generation is deſtroyed. So theſe not waiting in faith, ſingle in the begettings of God from above, to ſee in patience that formed, born and brought forth, but mixing with their reaſonings and wiſdom from below have not attained his appearance, but have turned the truth of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62425:41"/>
a lye, his glory into ſhame; wherefore God hath given them up to believe their own conceivings: And you hath he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into that glorious hope, and powerful faith, wherein you now ſtand; and them he hath left to be heirs of the corruptions of this world, which they have minded more than himſelf; where now many of them are the great oppoſers of his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, who were once called to bear a meaſure of his teſtimony in ſpiritual life and power.</p>
               <p>And now, dear friends, the called of God you are, unto the day of his coming, whoſe light hath ſhined out of darkneſs, giving you a knowledge in this great myſtery, and hope, and a power you have received from above, whereby you are come nearer the day than thoſe before you, and many have denied the world, and their Inheritance, that you might ſtand ſingle in hope thereof; Now the day is yours, if you be watchful, and faithful thereto, that you mix not with the earthly ſeed, nor bring forth a falſe birth, but that your hearts be ſingle, and open to receive him from above, the heavenly ſeed in the will of God, and not of your ſelves; the Son of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Fathers glory, who hath the living Image and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, to make all Sons and Daughters of the moſt High, conformable to himſelf, and heirs with him of the ſame Kingdome, glory, and power; even as many of you as ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, as to put him on as he is, and ſo walk in him as the begotten of God, Children of the moſt Holy, whom he hath counted worthy of ſo high a calling, as to receive his name, power, and glory, and to bear teſtimony what he is before all men, and to hold forth the power that you have in his name, and Image, above all names and forms in heaven or in earth; and this with all diligence, meekneſs, and fear, leſt Satan de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you of that ſimplicity that is in him, and ſo you come ſhort of his glory, and others be called. Now quit your ſelves as the beloved of God; caſt off every weight which would hinder your attaining him, that in the light is ſet before you; crucifie every affection after the earthly, and put away all the cares and pleaſures that would choak this ſeed, and whatever would mix in your minds, or plead for a place in your hearts, let it be to you as an accurſed thing, that the bleſſing of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:62425:42"/>
may come upon you, and through you to manifeſt to all the world, and that the holy name of Chriſt may be glorified in you, which hath long been polluted through ſuch as have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it in a contrary nature.</p>
               <p>For this is he to whoſe appearance in the World every tongue ſhall be made to confeſſe, and the Angels of God ſhall worſhip him, for he is the glory of God, and power of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in Heaven and in Earth, Gods love and good will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, and in him is the Father revealed, whom no eye hath ſeen. You that have received him, and hold him forth, are the light of the world, let him ſhine to the glory of your Father; It's you that hold forth the foundation of faith; he being lifted up will draw all men to him: hold him forth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as you receive him from above, and there is that in every Conſcience, that will anſwer to his appearance; for God hath not left him without witneſs: So that he that believes not is condemned already in himſelf, becauſe he believes not in that only begotten of God, whom the Father hath ſent into the world. If he do not that work in you, which none other can do, then how ſhould any believe, or confeſs that it is he. But at his appearance his works ſhall declare him, and leave all without excuſe.</p>
               <p>His Righteouſneſs, his meekneſs, his patient ſufferings, his lowly mindedneſs, his faith and obedience to the Father, his love and tender compaſſions towards all men, being richly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with all manner of godlineſs, ſhall declare him whoſe Image he bears, and whoſe Sonne he is, and from whence he comes, for the earth hath not thoſe fruits, power, and glory: Thus ſhall he be glorified in his Saints, and admired in all them that believe, and receive his teſtimony; And in this birth you ſhall not only ſave your ſelves, but hold forth Salvation to all that hear thereof.</p>
               <p>Wherefore as you profeſs that holy calling above others, ſo in the fear of God take heed what you bring forth, be ſober and watch diligently in that which is from above, leaſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy prevaile to mix ſomewhat of your own to hold forth in his name, that hath not the nature, power nor purity of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62425:42"/>
Son of God, and that being above, ſpoil you of his appearance, and mar the true Image, which you will find the envious one ſeeks to devour upon all occaſions, that alone having power over the head of the Serpent; wherefore ſee that you be cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him alone, as he is from heaven.</p>
               <p>But above all things, I beſeech you, put him on as he is the Son of Gods love, and ſo hold him forth towards all men, but eſpecially towards the brethren, ſo much the more as this being that which the enemy hath caſt long apon the children of light (to wit) want of love, taking his advantage while the way hath been preparing thereto, and the Spirit of Judgment and burning hath paſſed on the old building, a time of ſorrow, and pulling down, dreſſing the houſe where love ſhould dwell; ſo that though the root of the matter was in it, yet could not in that time ſpring forth towards others, nor indeed be fully ſhed abroad in the heart, while that is there which God hates: which love many have now received, and it is full time to bring forth, him ſo begotten in you, leſt any ſelfiſhneſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in his ſtead, and ſo prevent you of that which is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent; But that you all may put him on, as he is manifeſt from the Fathers boſome, and that you be cloathed therewith from heaven, ſo plentifully, that you may have to caſt over a Brothers nakedneſs, a garment of the ſame love, who came from above, to lay down his life for his enemies, and of the ſame power, who can forgive ſins and offences, above ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times a day, beholding each others with that good eye which waits for the ſoul and not for the ſin, which covers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes the evil with the good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat with him you may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in love, judging and receiving one another, in the increaſe of God, and not in that which is for deſtruction, giving more abundant honour to him that lacketh, that in the body be no ſchiſme, nor defile one another, nor keep alive a Brothers ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, nor blot out the name, and appearing of the holy ſeed in the leaſt, but keep the Lord in your eye, and the evils ſhall dye, and vaniſh away from amongſt you, and the appearance ſhall be the Lords, and to him ſhall the gathering of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be, hungry ſouls ſhall ſee, and be ſatisfied with his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62425:43"/>
likeneſſe, and all that behold his beauty ſhall confeſſe unto him, and in him ſhall the upright heart delight, for at his coming ſhall he eſtabliſh the Throne of Righteouſneſſe, and meaſure every appearance; and correct every falſe judgement, and that which enſnares the ſimple will he caſt out, for by the power of his appearance ſhall every thing be tryed, and peace proclaimed in the name of righteouſneſſe alone, for that which is not like him will not be able to ſtand before his appearance. But we know that when he appeares we ſhall be like him; he that hath this hope purifies himſelf even as he is pure, that he may be ſeen in him at his coming.</p>
               <p>Now dear friends, is your ſound gone to the ends of the earth, and God hath made you famous amongſt your enemies, in that you have begun to confeſs his name, and nature, and that he is in you whom many are looking for here, and there, and now the eyes of people and Nations are upon you to ſee your end, and now your glory is in putting him on, and cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you with him, a Lamb without blemiſh before God and man, that in him you may obtain good report, unreproveable, and holy, ſo ſhall you ſtop the way of the deſtroyer, and put an end to all falſe conceptions, and revive the hope of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Let his innocency be your armour, and put your truſt in his truth, for your Salvation. The time is full come for you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what he is to you, 'with boldneſs, with a confeſſion beyond words: for this appearance of him in love is that which ſhall judge all likeneſſes, and try all ſpirits, actions, judgments, and appearances, and by this ſhall you all be meaſured, what ſpirits you are of, and all ſpirits in the world, for he ſhall bring every hidden, formed, fained thing to light, at his coming, and what ever hath not this love in it, is not his, nor begotten of God, but he that hath this love is begotten of God, and hath him, the Father and the Son, the end of the Law and the Prophets, the ſubſtance and life of all knowledge, faith and works; the root and ground of every good gift, for herein are we made perfect in love, that we may have boldneſs in the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe we have put him on, &amp; dwell in him who is love, and as he is, ſo are we in this world. But he that loveth not
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62425:43"/>
is not made perfect in faith, in knowledge, in judgment, having not learned Chriſt herein, therefore by this he muſt be judged himſelf. So bleſſed is he that judges nothing before the time, who condemns not himſelf, wherein he judges another; all judgment being committed to him that can lay down his life for his enemies. Therefore happy are you if you have him on firſt, for when he appears his judgment is true, and ſhall ſtand, when all that hath come before him ſhall paſs away, for him alone hath the Father ſealed.</p>
               <p>So dearly beloved ones, my ſoul breaths towards you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that in all your ſeveral gifts, and adminiſtrations, this Son of God be your eye and end, the beauty and Glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the hope thereof to attain, may ſtay you in all try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als and temptations, knowing that in him alone is your laſting peace, and that which doth now befall you in all your afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is to ſhake all other appearances, that way may be made for him alone, whoſe Image and life, none can judge nor condemn. And the day is come, that happy is that man who hath nothing elſe to glory in, and this know that the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God in his own begotten, is your glory; and if any man boaſt himſelf and not herein, when he is weighed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he will be found wanting, the ſound thereof will not ſave him.</p>
               <p>As the ſame ſpirit from whence this comes, moves in any one, ſo let them ſend it abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the called of God, to be read and known.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:62425:44"/>
               <p>COme forth you children of light, come forth, depart out of the world, touch not the unclean thing, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one may make his appearance amongſt you: make haſt to the day of your God. If he ſhine forth, Salvation is with you, but he cannot appear in that heart where the world is retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If you be like the world it will own you; but that image which it receives not, is your everlaſting glory and beauty. So mind what works in the veſſel; for now muſt every Child appear like his Father, and muſt bring to light of what ſpirit he is begotten: and only bleſſed is he that comes in the name of the Lord, with power and great glory, that which the world is aſhamed of, is that with which the Son of God is glorified, and again muſt be glorified, he that bears the iniquities of men, and is fill'd with reproach, and yet appears without ſin, is our Saviour. And a Lamb without ſpot muſt take away the ſin of the world; his manifeſtation deſtroyes the work of the Devil; in a body prepared he delights to perform the councill of God, and to bring hidden things to light; that he may ſpeak myſteries to the wiſe therein, and hold forth a way to the ſimple, leading out of the ſnares of ſubtilty.</p>
               <p>Wherefore all that love his appearance, and ſeek the face of redemption, love that which prepares his way to his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in his Temple, that which breaks down the will of man, and as a fire goes before him; which is that baptiſme with which all that will receive him muſt be baptiſed into death. So when ſorrow, anguiſh, and tribulation comes upon you, rejoyce, and fly not. This comes to deſtroy nothing but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and to kill that which keeps you from eternal life, and to prepare a way for your peace, and a place for everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing righteouſneſs to dwell in you. For truly friends, in the threſhing floor muſt the Altar be ſet up, and where God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers by fire, there muſt his houſe be built: and as many as look to the end of this, may not deſpiſe correction, nor faint under the hand of reproof.</p>
               <p>That is good which brings down into the depth, where the wonders of God are learned, for he that will labour in Gods Vineyard muſt know every ſeed, and its root; what feeds it, and what famiſheth it, and the ground of every weed, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62425:44"/>
cauſe of every curſe. This many may ſee, when it's come to a Tree, brancheth, and brings forth fruit: but then its ſtrong and powerful, and not eaſily pluckt up, ſeldom got down without fire and much ſorrow, therefore bleſſed is that eye thats lowly, and diligent, which ſees every ſeveral appearance, that he may ſlay the ſeed of wickedneſs ere it bud, and not ſuffer the enmity to take root: for he that ſuffers divers ſeeds ſhall have ſorrow therein; and he that ſowes amongſt thornes and bryars muſt reap trouble; and where this kind is ſuffered to grow, there is torment to themſelves, and trouble to others; for how ſhould the thiſtle change its nature?</p>
               <p>So all that deſire peace, prepare a place that the ſeed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may grow alone, and the Sun thereof may ariſe and ſhine clearly, that nothing may grieve his holy ſpirit, for <hi>Jacob</hi> muſt dwell alone, and not be numbred among the reſt of the Nations, neither hath the Lamb fellowſhip with the beaſts of the field.</p>
               <p>Now as you have ſeen the Image of the earthly, and felt his power, and inclination to earthly things, captivating your minds downward, to things below: even ſo muſt you bear the Image of the Heavenly, if he reign that comes from above. Till then think not you are perfect, nor have attained to the reſurrection of the dead. For this I know of him, in whom your life is hid, that as he ariſeth, he ſhall as ſtrongly lead your mindes into the Heavenly, as ever you were captivated with the earthly. So he that can read the figure, rejoyce in hope concerning him that is to come; yet let none glory in the fight of this knowledge, but preſs into the life thereof, that God may be ſeen and glorified in you. For as he that hath gone much out with his mind, and hath drunk in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the earthly, is become the moſt ſubtle, ſelfiſh, and hard, and filled with all unrighteouſneſs, till he become incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: even ſo he that returns in, and drinks abundantly of the heavenly, doth become ſimple, innocent and harmleſs, ſeparate from all ungodlineſs, till he become incorruptible, and receive power to attain the Son of God, whoſe image de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the Father, from whence he is: for he that hath ſeen the Son, hath ſeen the Father, and he that hath the Son hath
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:62425:45"/>
the Father alſo. So, dear friends, behold the end of your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and glory of your profeſſion, your life in this world, and eternal inheritance, for the which to attain, we endure all things; for which ſufferings and patience, we have a cloud of witneſſes.</p>
               <p>So we follow not fables and fancies (as ſome ſuppoſe) but every one as he is proved herein, is able to ſet to his ſeal, even to the day of the Lord, with them that are gone before, whoſe ſpirits herein are perfected.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, dearly beloved of God, for his name ſake I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, be zealous for his appearance, and with meekneſs and fear inſtruct the ignorant, who oppoſe themſelves; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the weak; in all things leading with a life that cannot be blamed, knowing how manifold your labour of love is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in everlaſting glory, as he comes to be made manifeſt to the world. And the Lord God of power ſtrengthen all your hands by the appearance of his love; that, by the ſhedding of it abroad in your hearts, you may be made able to overcome the world, and willing to give your necks to the yoak of Chriſt, and to bear the burthens of the weak, till the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ariſe, and the body of Chriſt be perfected in one; that none of you ſuffer an evil eye or ear, which delights to behold the weakneſs of others; but that your whole delight be to wait for the appearance of God in all, and to behold his face in them, rather than their failings. And as this ariſes in every particular, it ſhall be a ſure token to you for good, and that you are paſſed from the love of evil, unto the love of God the Father, and the Son. And what you delight in, ſhall be your inheritance. And as you grow herein, ſo ſhall he whom you love to ſee, delight to make his appearance amongſt you, and to walk in you; and you ſhall not ſeek his face in vain, but with his likeneſs ſhall be ſatisfied, and ſhall praiſe the beauty of his appearance.</p>
               <p>Thus in honour preferring one another, you ſhall know, that the power of love is a miniſtration of life, to that which is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eloved.</p>
               <p>Who will be on the Lords part, now in this day of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when iniquity is growing to the full? and the manchild
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62425:45"/>
is to be born above it? And who will give up the veſſel to bear his name againſt the enmity that is now ariſing. And who will be glorified with the Lamb? Bleſſed and happy is he that is found worthy to follow him out of the world, bearing his reproach. To as many as receive him, he gives power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſons of God.</p>
               <p>But he that will bear his name muſt receive his nature, and himſelf alſo ſo walk, even as he walked; his name is power over ſin and the world. So the ſervants of ſin and the world cannot bear it; he that bears his name muſt bear it in his life and power, leſt he blaſpheme. Of fleſh and blood it is not born, nor by the will of man is it manifeſt, it is he that is born again, who hath his witneſs in himſelf, that muſt bear his name before the world for a witneſſe againſt them, who hath that life in him which teſtifies againſt the deeds thereof; but who bows thereto betrays him, and proves falſe in his teſtimony.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> in his houſe, made all things in likeneſſe of the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, ſo it became a Tabernacle of witneſſe to all the Nations (of the true God therein) and againſt all their falſe Gods, and falſe worſhips; and herein was he faithful to him that called him, and to all that beheld the pattern, he preached Gods preſence, dwelling in the Tabernacle made with hands. How much more muſt he that bears the name of Chriſt, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the pattern and ſuit his example, holding forth a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of witneſſe, and preaching the preſence of the true God therein, and againſt all the world, their falſe births, falſe ways and worſhips, herein proving faithful to him that hath called thereto, and to all that beholds, holding forth that holineſſe is his habitation here on earth, as it is in heaven, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a lively teſtimony thereof, by the Tabernacle of witneſſe, conformable to the heavenly example in all things. And to this end Chriſt deſcended, walked, and ſuffered on earth, leaving an example to all that follow his ſteps, wherein as in a lively Oracle God is found, in all that's builded after his image, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eek in his name and nature for the immortality that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therein. Now God was not to be found in the Tabernacle of <hi>Molech,</hi> (though ſought never ſo earneſtly) but in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of witneſſe, built according to the pattern; neither
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62425:46"/>
is he now to be found in the image of the world: nor is hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> name born in that nature though profeſſed never ſo zealouſly. Therefore let every one that nameth the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity; The ſeed of evil doers bears not the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Chriſt, but againſt him.</p>
               <p>Did they blaſpheme who ſaid they were Jews and were not? How much more do they who profeſſe the name of Chriſt, and are out of the vine, in a contrary nature?</p>
               <p>Wherefore all who aime to hold forth in life to his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and to attain his coming in purity and glory, muſt be diligent in the heavenly light, ever minding the way and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the holy Spirit, him that is from above, that his form you may ſee, who hath the heavenly image, and the holy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; that ſo beholding him with open face as in a glaſs, you may be changed into the ſame image, and formed thereafter, from glory to glory, by the powerful working of the ſame Spirit; until the Tabernacle be built conformable to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mple, and holy pattern in body and Spirit, that as he is, ſo may you be in this world, that God may appear in his Temple; that as the image of the earthly appeares in the world; ſo the image of the heavenly you may bear, a witneſſe againſt them. And by drinking in the communion of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, and power from above, you may become as able, zealous, and willing to hold forth the heavenly in holineſs, meekneſs, purity, patience, love, long-ſuffering, faith, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to God, and all the fruits of the Spirit, as the Sonnes of the world are to hold forth the earthly, in luſts and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſtrife and envy, cruelty, and oppreſſion, and all manner the works of the fleſh; that you may as truly and really, give up your bodies, minds, and ſtrength to ſuffer with Chriſt, that he may be manifeſt and magnified therein, in your mortal bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; (as others who are without God in the world, do give themſelves to act according to the principles and power of the God of this world, his unrighteous wayes, worſhips, and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all his curſed courſes, and the whole body of ſin, and myſtery of iniquity born in them.)</p>
               <p>And where the Tabernacle is thus edified, and the Temple thus cleanſed, there is a veſſel of honour, fit for the Maſters
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:62425:46"/>
uſe; that being filled with the holy Ghoſt, God may dwell on the earth, and take up his reſt therein, his Tabernacle being with men, the appearance of the bleſſed day, ſo many ſouls hunger for, and <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed longs to ſee, which the God of this world ſtrongly oppoſes, in all whoſe minds he hath blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and whole ſpirits he poſſeſſeth in diſobedience to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly light, for which the wrath of God remains upon that generation, till this day and for ever.</p>
               <p>Wherefore all you who wait for the Kingdom of God, and love his appearance, whoſe coming again is without ſin, abide within, and wait in that Temple where the witneſſe ariſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the world, that in faith and patience you may be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy to receive that witneſſe, that it may ariſe and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you, and that in bearing it you may come out of the world, being conformable to him, who ſuffered without the gates: bear his reproach, and you bear his name; touch not the unclean thing, and he will receive you for himſelf, in you to appear and be glorified; lifted up againſt the powers of darkneſſe. You that have received the earneſt of this Spirit, hath he not ſaid, I will dwell in you, and walk in you? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come out from among them and be you ſeparate. This is the joy that is ſet before you, to wit, his appearance, and that glory, for the attaining whereof, we endure the preſent ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and reproach; not to be compared therewith, for glory immortality, eternal life.</p>
               <p>O friends, who ſhall be found worthy at his coming, and in whom may he appear, and not conſume them? for our God is a conſuming fire; even in his holy Temple is he known, and with clean hands will he take up his reſt, and in the pure heart ſhall he be ſeen; elſe who may dwell with everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? and who may abide that baptiſme wherein every one ſhall be ſalted with fire at his coming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:62425:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>THere is a <hi>Spirit</hi> that I feel, that delights to do no <hi>Evil,</hi> nor to revenge any <hi>Wrong,</hi> but delights to endure all things, in <hi>Hope</hi> to enjoy its own in the End; Its hope is to outlive all <hi>Wrath</hi> and Contention, and to weary out all exaltation and Cruelty: or whatſoever is of Nature contrary to its ſelf, it ſees to the end of all temptations; as it bears no evil in it ſelfe, ſo is conceives none in thoughts to any other, For its ground and Spring is the Mercies and Forgiveneſſe of God; its Crown is <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> its Life is Everlaſting Love unfeigned, and takes its Kingdom with Intreaty, and not with Contention, and keeps it by Lowlineſſe of mind; in God alone it can rejoyce, though none elſe regard it, or can own its Life. Its conceived in Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and brought forth without any to pitty it, nor doth it murmur at Grief and Oppreſſion, it never rejoyceth but through Sufferings, for with the Worlds joy it is murthered; I found it alone being forſaken, I have fellowſhip therein, with them who lived in <hi>Dens,</hi> and Deſolate places in the Earth, who through Death Obtained this Reſurrection, and Eternal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Through the negligence of the Printer, and the diligence of that ſpirit that would not have truth and righteouſneſs to Reign; ſome faults have eſcaped, which the friendly Reader is deſired to correct, and not impute the blame to the Author, for herein he was blameleſs.</head>
            <p>In <hi>pag</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 1. for profeſſion <hi>r.</hi> poſſeſſion. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 21. for wherein <hi>r.</hi> where. <hi>p.</hi> 13. and laſt line, for the bodies. <hi>r.</hi> his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>l.</hi> 10. for here <hi>r.</hi> there. <hi>l.</hi> 38. for Eſtate <hi>r.</hi> ſtate. <hi>p.</hi> 17 <hi>l.</hi> 1. for or <hi>r.</hi> of. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 21. for, him <hi>r.</hi> them. <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 27. for, towards righteouſneſs <hi>r.</hi> towards Gods righteouſneſs. <hi>p.</hi> 26 <hi>l,</hi> 20. for mind <hi>r.</hi> wind, <hi>p. l.</hi> 32. for oorn <hi>r.</hi> born. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 3. for innocent paſs <hi>r.</hi> innocent cannot paſſe. <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>l.</hi> 7. this ſentence is left out <hi>[theſe reſiſted the ſpirit that ſpake in him] p.</hi> 48. <hi>l.</hi> 35. for our <hi>r.</hi> your. <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>l.</hi> 22. for the <hi>r.</hi> their. <hi>p.</hi> 53 laſt <hi>l.</hi> for mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>r.</hi> in meaſure. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> to come, and <hi>l.</hi> 25. for rooted <hi>r.</hi> blotted. <hi>p.</hi> 65. <hi>l.</hi> 9. for ſhe <hi>r.</hi> the. <hi>p.</hi> 72. <hi>l.</hi> 7. for, you ſouls <hi>r.</hi> your ſouls.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
